<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Holy things for holy men: or, The lawyers plea non-suited, his evidence proved insufficient, his foul mouth civilly wiped, and his arrogant railings admonished, and bridled; in some Christian reproofe and pitie expressed towards Mr Prynn's book; intituled, The Lord's supper briefly vindicated, (or rather indeed by him therein exposed, vilified, and profaned: and the conscientious ministry therein abused, injured, and affronted. By S.S. minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E946_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866638</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118915</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118915)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 141:E946[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Holy things for holy men: or, The lawyers plea non-suited, his evidence proved insufficient, his foul mouth civilly wiped, and his arrogant railings admonished, and bridled; in some Christian reproofe and pitie expressed towards Mr Prynn's book; intituled, The Lord's supper briefly vindicated, (or rather indeed by him therein exposed, vilified, and profaned: and the conscientious ministry therein abused, injured, and affronted. By S.S. minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the three Crowns, at the lower end of Cheapside, over-against the great Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.S. = Samuel Shaw.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is an advertisement for Tho. Parkhurst.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 18th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Lords supper briefly vindicated.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Holy things FOR HOLY MEN: OR, The Lawyers <hi>Plea Non-ſuited,</hi> his <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> proved <hi>inſufficient,</hi> his <hi>foul mouth ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy wiped,</hi> and his arrogant <hi>railings admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> and <hi>bridled;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN Some Chriſtian Reproofe and Pitie expreſſed towards M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> PRYNN'S Book; Intituled, <hi>The Lord's Supper briefly vindicated,</hi> (or rather indeed by him therein expoſed, vilified, and profaned: and the <hi>Conſcientious Miniſtry</hi> therein abuſed, injured, and affronted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By S. S. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Titus 1. 13.</bibl> 
               <hi>Rebuke them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 3. 14.</bibl> 
               <hi>But continue thou in the things which tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hast been aſſured of: knowing of whom thou haſt learned them.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mr. W. Pryn. Perpetuity,</hi> pag. 344.</bibl> The Sacraments do never convey any inward and ſpiritual grace, which may truly regenerate and engraft men into Chriſt: but where there is a hand of Faith to receive them, and the grace conveyed by them.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>Cupio propitiis auribus quid ſentiam dicere, ſin minus, dicam &amp; ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> Sen. Epiſt. 59.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the three Crowns, at the lower end of Cheapſide, over-againſt the great Conduit, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, And more eſpecially to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Will. Prynne <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
               </hi> While ſince I met an abſurd igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Pamphlet, under the name of one D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Swadlin,</hi> pleading for a <hi>Promiſcuous receiving the Lords Supper, by promiſcuous ſinners:</hi> (a Term as new, as unſound and ſilly.) I meant to have ſaid ſomewhat to his <hi>madneſs;</hi> But perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a later Pamphlet of his own, that he is <hi>Fame, &amp; infamia periturus:</hi> and that 'tis likely he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>ſuch trifles</hi> to get a <hi>miſerable living,</hi> I wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him; not thinking it ſtrange to read what I found there, becauſe they were <hi>his.</hi> Neither hath it coſt me any great expence of patience, to hear ſuch a <hi>Spittler</hi> as <hi>Joh. Spittlehouſe (in name and deed)</hi> call us <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> and all the ill-names that
<pb facs="tcp:118915:3"/> his worſe heart hath invented, and his loathſome throat ſpit forth againſt us. Neither have I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the <hi>ignorant blarings</hi> of ſo baſe and ſilly an <hi>Almanack-maker as Will. Lilly</hi> (not worth his worthleſs profeſſion.) I can as eaſily ſlight the ravings of <hi>Papiſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and pitiful Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited <hi>Quakers,</hi> as the Lion the bawlings and yap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of a little Cur,</p>
            <p>But to ſee <hi>a petty-martyr, an old Profeſſor,</hi> and <hi>a learned one,</hi> even a <hi>Mr. Prynne</hi> to fall from his own ſtedfaſtneſs, to behold him watching over us like a <hi>Leopard,</hi> and helping the Sons of <hi>Lot;</hi> and hear him, <hi>even him,</hi> uſing (as <hi>Mr. John Goodwin</hi> called it) <hi>the very language of Dragons againſt us,</hi> this grievs once for all! and ſick as I am, I cannot but ſay to him, as <hi>dying Caeſar</hi> to his <hi>Brutus, Etiam &amp; tu Prynne!</hi> What is our <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt ſuch <hi>Prophets?</hi> even ſuch Prophets as the <hi>old Prophet was,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. will he bring us into a <hi>praemunire againſt God,</hi> and our <hi>high truſt and calling;</hi> whilſt he tells us a <hi>fair tale</hi> of what is our duty to do and indure, when we find not one word for it <hi>in our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I firſt ſaw <hi>Mr. Prynns book of the Lords Supper vindicated</hi> (in the Title), (which
<pb facs="tcp:118915:3"/> came to my hand ſome few daies ſince) I beheld it with ſuch a ſpirit as <hi>Paul the Athenians Altar to the Unknown God;</hi> for I perceive <hi>Mr. Prynne</hi> doth <hi>adore a conceit of he knows not what,</hi> whilſt under the <hi>Inſcription of Vindication,</hi> hee defameth, profaneth, and proſtituteth the bleſſed Sacrament. Therefore whilſt he gives the empty name of a <hi>Vindication</hi> to his book: let him give me leave to do the thing, to vindicate the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> indeed, from all <hi>wicked, unholy, bold intruders</hi> and <hi>uſurpers:</hi> and wherein he ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtakes himſelf I will declare unto him: (if he <hi>Pleaſe to truſt me as willingly in mine, as I would him in his Profeſſion.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Book I am very ſenſible of his <hi>change of Spirit,</hi> ſince he wrote <hi>his uſeful Book of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the regenerate:</hi> had ſome man then ſhewed him ſuch a Book <hi>as this of his,</hi> and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etold him; <hi>You</hi> ſhall one day write thus, he would have cried out, <hi>What, am I a Dogg, that I ſhould do ſuch a thing!</hi> Then <hi>he would have plucked out his eies,</hi> for the godly Miniſters zealous of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: but now <hi>they are become his enemies, becauſe we tell him the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hereunto I cannot but note his <hi>fury, railing, impertinencies, and falſe principles</hi> in his book;
<pb facs="tcp:118915:4"/> and have laid down better: not from my own judgment, but from <hi>former and later judicious ſound Divines, at home, and abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have alſo obſerv'd his <hi>pomp and confidence</hi> the matter and form of his whole book: and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelf, I have dared gently to prick his rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling full blown bladder, to conſider the paint of this <hi>Butterfly,</hi> the feather of this <hi>Oſtrich,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſquallid wings of this <hi>flitter-mouſe:</hi> whereby I can eaſily judge (according to the old rule) <hi>Qui ſe habet pro ſapiente, hunc Deus &amp; homines habent pro ignaro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the profest refutation of the Book, I do not look upon it as my work. I know the Lawyer hath <hi>learned and pious Antagoniſts,</hi> with whom I number not my ſelf in point of ability, (yet a ſmal meaſure might be ſufficient to anſwer 100 ſuch <hi>Pamphlets;</hi> or any other that I have had the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſee upon their ſubject.)</p>
            <p>My preſent writing (and further I never intend) is onely to enter my <hi>diſſent and proteſt,</hi> (and not without good evidence to the truth) againſt <hi>Mr. Pryns</hi> erroneous conceit: for which I am grieved, and for the reproaches he caſts upon <hi>conſcientious Miniſters, (for the reproaches of thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached them are fallen upon me)</hi> whilſt our
<pb facs="tcp:118915:4"/> enemies rejoice that they have found our friend and Brother to be an Executioner, (rather to grieve then torment us,) that they have gotten our <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> to write angry <hi>Philippicks</hi> againſt us; even our own <hi>Prynne</hi> to implead us, and open his mouth againſt us, with a <hi>tongue of falſhood, and compaſſe us about with words of hatred, and fight againſt us without a cauſe: for our love he is our adverſary, but we give our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praier!</hi> (vide Pſal. 109.) <hi>and our praiers return into our own boſome;</hi> our hearts are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, his ſpittings upon us are wiped off: and ſoul-eſtabliſhing conſolations and promiſes are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, to the condition, calling, and perſon of every <hi>godly Miniſter. They ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not prevail againſt the; for I am with thee, ſaith the Lord, to deliver thee,</hi> Jer. 1. 19. <hi>In nothing terrified by your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which to them is an evident token of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but to you of ſalvation, and that of God,</hi> Phil 1. 28 (vide Genev. &amp; Bezae not as) <hi>I know thy works, behold, I have ſet before thee an open door, and no man can ſhut it; for thou haſt a little ſtrength, and haſt kept my word, and not denied my name. Behold I will make them of the Synagogue of Satan; which</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118915:5"/> 
               <hi>ſay they are Jews, and are not, but do lie: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I will make them to come and worſhip before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee. Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience, I will alſo keep thee from the hour of temptation, which ſhall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth. Behold I come quickly, hold that faſt which thou haſt, that no man take thy Crown,</hi> Rev. 3. 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have no more to add, but</hi> Beza<hi>'s ſhort E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to his</hi> Diallacton, <hi>which I ſhall apply to my ſelf in this work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pacem aliorum quaerere pulchrum eſt, &amp; habet certam promiſſionem; <hi>Beati Pacifici.</hi> Sed vereor, hoc dum cupide ſector, ne quod eis qui pugnas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruunt evenire ſolet, idem mihi quoque accidat, Illi dum aliorum ſaluti conſulunt, ipſi reportant vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera: &amp; ego dum id operam ut diſſidentes rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aent in gratiam, ab i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſdem fortaſſe nullam inibo gratiam. Id ſi fit, illius exemplo me levabo, qui dixit: ſi hominibus placuiſſem, Chriſti ſervus non eſſem. Vale, ac ſtude Chriſto placere.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118915:5"/>
            <head>Holy things FOR HOLY MEN: OR, The Lawyers <hi>Plea Non-ſuited,</hi> his <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> proved <hi>inſufficient,</hi> his <hi>foul mouth ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy wiped,</hi> and his arrogant <hi>railings admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> and <hi>bridled,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot give a better cenſure of M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>Pryns</hi> late Pamphlet, then this; That 'tis <hi>a little Book, and a great miſchief:</hi> the ſhame of the <hi>Author,</hi> the grief of the <hi>Godly,</hi> the ſtrengthening of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> and the wonderment of <hi>all;</hi> and this I ſpeak from what I have beheld and read therein.</p>
            <p>He ſtileth his Book, <hi>The Lords Supper Vindicated;</hi> which makes me remember the old ſaying, <hi>Tituli reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, Pyxides venenum;</hi> for there is indeed <hi>Vindication</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118915:6"/> in the <hi>Title,</hi> but <hi>Profanation</hi> in the <hi>drift</hi> and <hi>event.</hi> That kind of noble folly is fallen upon him, that a Philoſopher ſpeaks of <hi>(Non eſt Ignobilis gradus ſtultitiae, vel ſi neſcias quiddicas, tamen velle de rebus propoſitis, hanc vel illam partem ſtabilire:)</hi> To undertake ſomething in things on foot, though to little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In the peruſal of his book, I have chiefly obſerved <hi>Three things;</hi> his <hi>ſhameleſs railing; his weak imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and failing proof that he brings to confirm his opinion, and his groundleſſe aſſertions;</hi> all which I could not let paſſe, without ſuch an <hi>Item</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> gives <hi>Petilian, Mira dicitis, nova dicitis, falſa dicitis: Mira ſtupemus, nova ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veamus, falſa convincimus. You ſpeak ſtrange things, new things, falſe things: The ſtrange things we admire, the new we beware, and the falſe we confute.</hi> And upon all we <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, reprove,</hi> and <hi>adviſe,</hi> leaſt the <hi>unhappy Author</hi> ſhould in all this, <hi>be wiſe in his own conceit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> (I ſay) I have obſerved <hi>(inſulſa &amp; jejuna convicia) his outragious, groſſe, and inſolent reproaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt conſcientious Miniſters, their perſons and doctrine.</hi> Many beſides him have taken that irreverend licence, as <hi>Arminians, Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. but (as to barbarous baſe procacious ſcurrility) Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> hath ſurpaſſed them all.</p>
            <p>And that you may <hi>ſee and hate</hi> ſuch <hi>ſordid vomits,</hi> I have (though loth to foul my Pen) tranſcribed ſome of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> that are contrary to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, <hi>he termeth Noveliſts, Politick charmers,</hi> pag. 2. <hi>New Doctors,</hi> pag. 6. <hi>Audacious, a generation of Novellers,</hi> p. 32. <hi>Liers, Impoſtors, new Dogmatiſts, Lord Keepers of the great Seal of heaven, who refuſe to ſet thoſe Seals where God hath preſcribed them; as more wiſe, holy, carefull of their profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and nullity, then God himſelf,</hi> pag. 13. <hi>Hard-hearted,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118915:6"/> 
               <hi>uncharitable, obſtinate, domineering Miniſters, domineering Tyrants, renouncing the chief part of their Miniſterial fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and profest Apoſtates from the Doctrine and practice of Chriſts Apoſtles, primitive Fathers, Churches, Chriſtians, Miniſters of Chriſt throughout the world in former ages,</hi> p. 57 and p. 88. we find almoſt a whole page loaden with ſuch fruit of curſing and ſlander; Theſe are but <hi>a few of the wounds</hi> that we receive from <hi>our friend, in whoſe calamity we put on ſackcloth, and behaved our ſelves as if he had been a friend or a brother, and went heavily as one that mourneth for his mother.</hi> This is a practick part of <hi>Machievills poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;</hi> this is ſome of the <hi>deadly ſome</hi> that works out of Mr. <hi>Pryns mouth,</hi> in this fit of his <hi>falling ſickneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ſpeeds the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>conſcientious Miniſters,</hi> better then their <hi>perſons.</hi> He calls their <hi>doctrine</hi> that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his conceit, <hi>Falſ, vain, abſurd, dangerous ſpreading error, a ſelf-intereſt againſt the inſtitution of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> (Epiſt. to Reader) <hi>an Anti-ſacramental, abſurd, impious Paradox, Pharaſaïcal ſpreading leaven and Gangreen,</hi> p. 1. <hi>A Cuckows ſong,</hi> p. 13. <hi>pure non-ſenſe in Divinity,</hi> p. 14. <hi>Soul-ſtarving cruelty,</hi> p. 20. <hi>Soul-murthering crime,</hi> p. 18. <hi>A moſt abſurd, unchriſtian, untheological, erroneous, if not blaſphemous aſſertion.</hi> Theſe are but a few <hi>gleanings</hi> of that <hi>Harveſt</hi> of his, that repleniſhes his book in a moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious manner. This is the <hi>colour of</hi> Mr. Pryns <hi>tongue, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed red in the reputation of the Saints.</hi> Behold here the growth of ill weeds in a good ſoil! Is it not pity to ſee <hi>Jordane</hi> fall into ſuch a <hi>ſea of Sodom,</hi> to ſee a man in <hi>reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for wiſdom</hi> (with the fooliſh <hi>Emperor</hi> to make ſhew of ſo many <hi>Spiders,</hi> to boaſt the greatneſs of his City) to ſhew the greatneſs of his <hi>reading</hi> by the badneſſe of his <hi>choice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, I never believed Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> had had ſo foul a ſtomach, till I beheld and loathed the filthy vomit of that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118915:7"/> book of his. Far be it from us, to ſtudy <hi>ſo baſe a language,</hi> as to return railing for railing: good <hi>breeding, civility,</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> hath taught us better. Better it is (and yet it grievs us to do it) to ſpread his book before the Lord, with the perplexed words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>This thou hast ſeen, O Lord; for thou beholdeſt miſchief and ſpite, to requite it with thy hand, &amp;c.</hi> For Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> himſelf I ſhall onely tell him (as <hi>Auſtin Petilian) Whilſt he willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdraws from our reputation, he unwillingly adds to our reward:</hi> and as learned <hi>Beza</hi> anſwered, That <hi>Cyclops He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuſius, &amp; Illyricus (Haec vero cujus culpâ eveniant, vide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dominus &amp; judicabit. At <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e neque Deus, neque homines (niſi ſerio reſipueris) à tot calumniis, &amp; foediſſimis menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis abſolverit: God will ſee and judge where the fault lieth, and truly neither God nor men will ever forgive ſuch calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and ſtinking ſlanders,</hi> except you repent. And let Mr <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynne</hi> remember, that hard ſpeeches have judgment following them: And if to call a brother <hi>Raca, and fool, be in danger of hell fire,</hi> to call <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Paſtors of the Church of Chriſt Liers, Impoſtors,</hi> &amp;c. bringeth the <hi>Railer</hi> into danger of <hi>ſomething.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The praiſe that the <hi>Biſhop of Lincoln</hi> worthily gave <hi>King James,</hi> (Funeral Sermon <hi>May</hi> 7. 1625. <hi>pag.</hi> 51.) may be the inglorious Trophey of Mr. <hi>Prynne: (However he lived awongſt Puritans, and was kept as a Ward under them, yet he deſpiſed their opinion;</hi> ſo) what ever Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> hath pleaded for <hi>Puritans,</hi> and <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious men,</hi> (ſee his <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> in <hi>Epiſt.</hi> and his <hi>Hiſtrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix)</hi> yet you ſee now, this <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> hath the <hi>Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy;</hi> (Let me not ſay, an <hi>evil heart hath deceived him,</hi> but) hee's retained on the other ſide, (whilſt he makes <hi>a wide mouth</hi> at us) he bears the beſt <hi>affection</hi> to the <hi>worſt caſe,</hi> and doth now but deſpiſe what formerly he <hi>printed</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118915:7"/> 
               <hi>and profeſſed.</hi> I ſee it, and am ſorry that ſuch <hi>great wits,</hi> and <hi>great parts,</hi> often fall into great <hi>madneſs, (magna ingenia, magnas dementias)</hi> and the greater age and height a man attaineth unto, the greater and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous is his fall, <hi>when he lets go his hold.</hi> Let no man therefore think himſelf ſafe, but <hi>ſtrengthen himſelf in the Lord, and the knowledg and obedience of the Goſpel:</hi> Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill that he reads upon Mr. <hi>Pryn's books,</hi> that which ſome found upon the Statue of <hi>Zenacherib, Look to me, and learn to be godly:</hi> to be <hi>ſtedfaſt,</hi> to hold the truth <hi>in love;</hi> and let him that <hi>thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leaſt he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why (amongſt many reproaches) are we ſo often and again in his book branded for ſelf-ſeekers? The man goes <hi>barefoot</hi> himſelf, and yet planteth <hi>thorns;</hi> hee's made of <hi>glaſſe,</hi> and yet <hi>throws ſtones at others:</hi> A man clad in <hi>Birdlime,</hi> crieth out againſt <hi>ſelf-interest!</hi> Shall I ſay, <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer cure thy ſelf?</hi> Shall I cry out in a paſſion, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> once did? <hi>Hodie Proh! dolor! juris Prudentia ex matrona facta est meretrix, ex regina tyranna, ex matre noverca!</hi> No, verily! good manners, and better experience of ſome <hi>honorable perſons of</hi> Mr. Pryns <hi>ſociety,</hi> and of many of his <hi>Profeſſion</hi> have told me, that <hi>worth,</hi> and <hi>deſert,</hi> and <hi>nobleneſs,</hi> deſervs and commands reſpect in all.</p>
            <p>The profeſſion of the <hi>Law</hi> is good, if a man uſe it <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully:</hi> but yet the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is <hi>better,</hi> and the <hi>faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of it <hi>(as low as we are)</hi> are too high for the reach of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> ſcurrility and procacity.</p>
            <p>Truly the Slander that Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> is pleaſed to deform us with, in the day of his <hi>ſin,</hi> and our <hi>reproach,</hi> is ſuch, as neither would be alleged by the <hi>Divel,</hi> nor <hi>wicked men</hi> for the very <hi>incredibleneſs</hi> of it. For if we be <hi>ſelf-ſeekers,</hi> 'tis we, and not our <hi>office,</hi> and <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry.</hi> Is it <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118915:8"/> to procure <hi>adverſaries?</hi> To rebuke, reprove, and reject; Daring and confident ſpirits, that are thereby provoked againſt us? Is it <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> to put on the ſpirit of an <hi>Elias,</hi> a <hi>Jeremy,</hi> or a <hi>Chryſoſtome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have alwaies feared that <hi>flattery</hi> and <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> had rather been <hi>whelps</hi> (Mr. <hi>Pryn's</hi> expreſſion) <hi>of the ſame Litter:</hi> I thought that <hi>to crie peace, peace,</hi> and <hi>to heal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully,</hi> and <hi>daubing with untempered mortar,</hi> had been <hi>ſelf-ſeeking: to ſay to the wicked</hi> (by inviting or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him in his prophaneneſs to the <hi>Lords Supper) it ſhall go well with him,</hi> had been <hi>ſelf-ſeeking:</hi> If this be to bee <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>ſelf ſeeking,</hi> we will be more <hi>vile and ſelf-ſeeking:</hi> It is our <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>honor,</hi> and <hi>duty;</hi> 'tis our evidence of <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> in our <hi>Stewardſhip</hi> both before <hi>God</hi> and <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall follow the game no further upon this <hi>ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent,</hi> that his Rancorous <hi>breath</hi> hath left, but do hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh him a <hi>better tongue,</hi> &amp; a <hi>milder ſpirit!</hi> and if he be indeed <hi>better,</hi> &amp; <hi>learneder</hi> then other men; he ought to be the more <hi>modeſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>inoffenſive:</hi> not full of <hi>ferocity</hi> &amp; <hi>rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> giving ſuch great, &amp; juſt offence to the <hi>Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second thing</hi> I have obſerved in his <hi>book;</hi> is his <hi>weak, impertinent,</hi> and <hi>failing proof;</hi> which he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for his <hi>grace begetting ſoul Converting way.</hi> we know the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are indeed the holy, and ſoul-eſtabliſhing <hi>Word of God,</hi> and proofs from thence <hi>ſitly applyed,</hi> are <hi>like apples of Gold in pictures of Silver:</hi> But as the <hi>wringing the noſe bringeth forth blood,</hi> ſo wreſting, and forcing <hi>the Scripture,</hi> extenuateth the <hi>Proof.</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> hath brought <hi>above</hi> 500 <hi>quotations</hi> into view, about his <hi>opinion,</hi> in his little Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet: but not ſo much as any <hi>one evidence</hi> given by <hi>any</hi> of them; but a ſlight vapor he maketh of what ſome <hi>good men</hi> have granted; <hi>that 'tis poſſible that Converſion may be wrought</hi> (upon ſome perſons) <hi>at the Lords Table,</hi> p. 25. How poor a ſhift is this (after he hath filled his book with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118915:8"/> with <hi>quotations,</hi> as full as the <hi>Turks</hi> their <hi>ditches</hi> and <hi>tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> with their <hi>ſlaves</hi> and captive <hi>Souldiers)</hi> to argue from what God in his <hi>Infinite mercy</hi> and <hi>prerogative</hi> may do; to our <hi>duty</hi> what we <hi>muſt do!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall give you ſome <hi>Inſtances,</hi> of his <hi>distortings</hi> and <hi>miſapplications,</hi> and yet by him conceited to be the moſt <hi>pat, preſt,</hi> and <hi>convincing</hi> Proofs in all his book.</p>
            <p>He undertakes to prove, <hi>that the Apoſtles admitted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to the Lords Supper,</hi> pag. 11. <hi>from Acts</hi> 2. 44. 46. Is it not a <hi>convincing</hi> proof? and to the <hi>Purpoſe?</hi> yet ſuch kind of proofs are conſtantly produced <hi>(quidlibet ex quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, pag. 12. 38, 39. <hi>he ſaith, theſe Scriptures prove</hi> (viz. 1 Cor. 10. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and verſ. 16, 17. and 1 Cor. 12. 12. 13.) <hi>The Lords Supper to be a converting, grace-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting Ordinance; and that all baptized Chriſtians ought to receive the Sacramentall ſeal of the Lords Supper: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſecluding any, for ignorance, ſcandall, unregeneracy, or want of ſaving grace; the univerſality of all Chriſtians have right to, and actuall duty in, Communicating together at the Lords Supper.</hi> Thus doth he <hi>impriſon the truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe!</hi> who ever hath bin ſo confident as Mr. <hi>Prin?</hi> to aſſert, <hi>that none baptized, are to be excluded from the Lords Supper?</hi> at leaſt, who ever hath been ſo <hi>ſhameleſs,</hi> as to bring ſuch <hi>Scriptures</hi> to prove it, as never had any the leaſt <hi>acquaintance</hi> with his conceit?</p>
            <p>He produceth <hi>pag.</hi> 38 another Proof, from <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27. to 53, (a good long Proof) <hi>and ſaith, that not onely moſt Popiſh writers wholly, but all Protestant writers, equally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Lords Supper,</hi> and is not this his huge, bold, ignorant <hi>confidence? when as Proteſtant writers</hi> declare the contray <hi>(Muſt. ad Loc. manifeſtum eſt, non loqui Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num hoc loco de Sacrament ali carnis ſuae eſu, &amp;c.) it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118915:9"/> 
               <hi>that our Saviour in this place (ſaith Muſc.) ſpeaks not of the Sacramental eating of his fleſh.</hi> Of the ſame mind is <hi>Chemnitius, Rollock,</hi> and the <hi>later laborious Hutchinſon;</hi> The <hi>Engliſh Annotations, Diodat, Fulk, and Cartwright,</hi> in their anſwers to the <hi>Remiſh Teſtament. Proteſtant wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> that have the <hi>clear mind</hi> of all the reſt. But ſurely M. <hi>Pryn</hi> conceivs us <hi>unacquainted</hi> with <hi>Protestant writers,</hi> or too lazy to follow him and convince his <hi>impertinent quotations.</hi> Let any that <hi>underſtandeth,</hi> judg whether thoſe words, <hi>Whoſoever eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath everlaſting life,</hi> be properly applyed to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenrates eating;</hi> of whom (I tremble to ſpeak it) the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>they eat and drink damnation to themſelves.</hi> Learned and copious <hi>Gerhard, de ſacra coena, cap.</hi> 21 <hi>num.</hi> 229 <hi>ſaith, Dictum Johannis Cap.</hi> 6. 53. <hi>non de ſacramentali, ſed ſpirituali corporis &amp; ſangninis Chriſti manducatione, &amp; bibitione tractat.</hi> And the like I might transſcribe for <hi>many others,</hi> yet <hi>this of John</hi> is the place, that is M. <hi>Pryns invincible evidence</hi> (and <hi>that all Proteſtant divines apply it ſo;) That Christ doth ordinarily work true converſion in mens ſouls, in a proper ordinary way, by his Supper duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, as he doth by the word Preached, or any other means of grace.</hi> I appeal to the <hi>learned</hi> to conſider of the <hi>diſ-ingenuity</hi> of the proof he pretendeth to; when he hath <hi>not a word</hi> (that I find) for the true evidence of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Yet that you may ſee more of his <hi>trifling,</hi> (even in <hi>holy things.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See <hi>p.</hi> 38. and 52. what <hi>Signall proof</hi> he brings us <hi>for the ſame;</hi> from Joh. 1. 12. <hi>To as many as received him, to them he gave power to become the ſons of God.</hi> Will M. <hi>Pryn</hi> call in <hi>Proteſtant writers</hi> to ſtand by him here alſo? to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm with him, <hi>Therefore, this Sacrament and the Word are both alike regenerating, converting Ordinances?</hi> and ſee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118915:9"/> 
               <hi>pag.</hi> 42, a like proof he fetches <hi>(at a venture)</hi> from <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 17. <hi>That the Sacrament hath power to turn them from ſin,</hi> &amp; <hi>Satan, unto God; and muſt of neceſſity be granted by all, to be a ſoul-converting, faith-engendring Ordinance.</hi> Who can ever bear ſuch <hi>reaſonings</hi> and <hi>proofs,</hi> (diſſonant from all ſhew of proof at all, to the matter in hand) in ſuch <hi>great</hi> and high concernment <hi>of the Goſpell?</hi> how <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorly</hi> doth he apply all theſe ſweet and heavenly promiſes of grace, (ſee his pag. 43, 44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 45) <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 74 75. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 9, 10, 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 25, <hi>and the reſt;</hi> to prove, <hi>that the Lords supper muſt needs be a grace-begetting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and proper to the unregenerate?</hi> And yet he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>that the approach unto it is a hunger, thirſt, asking, ſeeking, knocking, watching at the gates of wiſdome, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the ways, and drinking in the rain of Gods grace.</hi> If this be <hi>ſence in divinity,</hi> or honeſt <hi>dealing with Scripture,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> hath no <hi>non-ſence</hi> in his <hi>writings.</hi> Let me ask him, where he hath found ſuch <hi>ſanctified properties</hi> in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſons? if to ſeek, <hi>knock, watch, thirſt, hunger, drink in the rain of Gods grace</hi> bee the <hi>Propertie of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſon,</hi> we may all wiſh to be <hi>unregenerate:</hi> but I am ſure Mr. <hi>Pryns expreſſions,</hi> and all the like, are <hi>unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate,</hi> and <hi>illegitimate</hi> both, and not to be <hi>indured;</hi> and yet 'tis pitty to ſpend <hi>ink,</hi> and <hi>paper,</hi> and <hi>precious time</hi> to <hi>refute him:</hi> but that, elſe we ſhall be accounted <hi>idle,</hi> and <hi>unable</hi> (as ſome have boaſted) to anſwer him.</p>
            <p>What can ever be imagined more <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>frivolous,</hi> then almoſt all his quotations, which he bids us <hi>note, pag.</hi> 48, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about the <hi>ſight</hi> that an <hi>unregenerate</hi> man hath of the <hi>Ordinances of God, and of Chriſt in the Supper? Bleſſed are your eyes, for they ſee</hi> Mat. 5. 16. <hi>Let me ſee thy face, and hear thy voyce, Cant.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>with abundance of the like:</hi> all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118915:10"/> which he applies to the <hi>unregenerate in the Sacrament, and ſaith, by theſe premiſes it is moſt clearly demonſtrated, that the Lords Supper is a ſoul-converting, grace-begetting Ordinance.</hi> If this be not <hi>prophaning of holy thing's,</hi> ſurely there is no ſuch ſin amongſt men. It might be expected, that the naming of ſuch <hi>abſurdities,</hi> might be confutation ſufficient unto <hi>a wiſe man: (As for example,</hi> the very <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> of the Scripture whereby) <hi>pag.</hi> 56, he doth <hi>perſwade</hi> us, (after a moſt <hi>outragious, long, ungracious</hi> and moſt <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill railing,</hi> in the former page) nay would <hi>enforce us,</hi> to give the <hi>Lords Supper to ignorant, vitious, unregenerate ones:</hi> he quoteth <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. 41, 42, 45. <hi>I was hungry, and yee gave me no meat; I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink;</hi> this his proof; (with many others, juſt as pertinent,) that he introduceth for the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>O moſt Holy ſacred <hi>Scriptures!</hi> how am I pierced and afflicted, to ſee you thus <hi>wracked, diſtorted, diſmembred,</hi> by the <hi>paſſions</hi> and <hi>violent conceits</hi> of men! I cannot bear it, and yet I muſt behold it before my face! and M. <hi>Pryn</hi> the moſt <hi>unhappy,</hi> and to be <hi>lamented executioner!</hi> Ah Lord! This is far a more <hi>horrid ſight,</hi> then the <hi>wicked and mercileſs</hi> ſlitting of <hi>noſes,</hi> and cropping of <hi>ears,</hi> and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>cheeks</hi> of worthfull men! (for which thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> overtook many:) And ſhall we not think <hi>&amp; alio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manet ultor,</hi> That God is highly <hi>aiſpleaſed</hi> with thoſe <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi> and (as to goſpel knowledge) <hi>unlearned ones,</hi> that will even dare to <hi>wreſt, mangle, tear,</hi> and <hi>abuſe</hi> the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> to their own <hi>deſtruction!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that all may ſee, that I have not dealt <hi>too ſharply:</hi> Let them (that have the <hi>patience)</hi> read what he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>pag.</hi> 9, 10. 32, 38. <hi>from Ezek.</hi> 11. 18. 19. 20. <hi>and cap.</hi> 36. 25, 26. <hi>and from Jer.</hi> 32. 39. (Gods promiſe of creating or giving a <hi>new heart.</hi> (Theſe are all <hi>ſubpaena'd,</hi> to prove
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118915:10"/> the <hi>Lords Supper to be a faith-engendring, ſoul couverting Ordinance; where there is no pre-exiſtent grace,</hi> and from theſe Scriptures it muſt follow, <hi>(as he will have them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded)</hi> that if the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> be a <hi>ſeal,</hi> it muſt be a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating, and ſoul converting Ordinance.</hi> Theſe are his <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>judicious plain proofs</hi> for his opinion. That 'tis a <hi>ſeal,</hi> and conveieth <hi>new</hi> and further <hi>grace,</hi> we all affirm; as to the <hi>meaſure,</hi> but not to the <hi>nature,</hi> and firſt principle of <hi>grace:</hi> as food bringeth <hi>new renewed life,</hi> by way of <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment,</hi> not <hi>begetteth new life,</hi> where it was not at all <hi>in the firſt principle.</hi> I ſhall ever pray for a <hi>new heart,</hi> and a <hi>renued mind,</hi> and yet believe (whilſt I pray for them) that I have (thorow grace) in ſome meaſure <hi>received</hi> them: but I would yet have theſe <hi>ſweet and heavenly promiſes,</hi> more and more fulfilled to me, and fully evidenced in me.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewen a few of the Scriptures, that are put upon the <hi>Tally on</hi> M. <hi>Prynns part; to prove the Lords Supper a converting Ordinance.</hi> Yet pag. 7. <hi>he intreateth us to confine our ſelvs to Scripture language.</hi> (I would this old <hi>Crab</hi> would go right himſelfe, that fairly teacheth us (like the <hi>ſhell-fiſh in the fable)</hi> to go ſo ſtraight,) This of his I think is the guiſe of all <hi>our oppoſites; Arrians, Papiſts, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, Anti-Trinitarians,</hi> to intreat and adjure us, to keep cloſe to <hi>Scripture</hi> (a piece of counſell for ever and from any to be embraced) whilſt they (as M. <hi>Prynne</hi> here <hi>gallopeth</hi> over <hi>five or ſix hundred places of Scripture,</hi> like a <hi>wild horſe</hi> over a field of corn,) range, and ſpoil all, no man knowing how they could <hi>break into</hi> ſuch quotations. If any man of a wel grounded judgment in Scripture mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, can find ſtrength and validity in his <hi>quotations,</hi> I have named, I will hereafter lay my hand on my <hi>mouth</hi> &amp; be <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for ever;</hi> &amp; ſhal from henceforth perſwade my ſelf, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118915:11"/> the <hi>fooliſh ſhaveling</hi> had a good proof from <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 16. to evidence that the <hi>Pope</hi> is above the <hi>Emperour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall now (in the third place) proceed to his bold and groundleſs aſſertions.</hi> By which we may judge, that it was more his <hi>confidence</hi> then his <hi>diſcretion,</hi> that hath <hi>ruſhed</hi> him upon ſuch <hi>abſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dities</hi> and <hi>wild con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits. Scaliger</hi> tells us <hi>(In homine docto, tria omnino excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere debent, morum integritas at que civilitas, eruditio varia ac multa, ingenium ſummum cum accerrimo judicio conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,)</hi> a learned man ſhould have intire good manners, and civility, various, and much learning, and a high wit, joined wit a piercing judgment.</p>
            <p>You have had Mr. <hi>Prynns integrity, good manners,</hi> and <hi>civility</hi> expreſſed freely, againſt the <hi>conſcientious Miniſters</hi> before his <hi>multiplicity</hi> &amp; <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>reading</hi> (if his Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had been right applyed) in the quotations of <hi>places cited,</hi> of which we have had a taſt (an <hi>unſavory</hi> one.) Now to his <hi>(Ingenium ſummun, cum accerrimo judicio cujunctum)</hi> high and huge wit and judgment. Where I wiſh I could juſtifie <hi>the latter,</hi> as I can affirm <hi>the former.</hi> But I hope this is but his <hi>diſeaſe of his fancy,</hi> and ſome <hi>diſtemper,</hi> and <hi>heat</hi> (and not a perfect <hi>calenture)</hi> of his conceit; that may prove <hi>curable;</hi> and that 'tis not the very <hi>conſtitution</hi> of his ſerious and more conſiderate <hi>ſoul.</hi> I do wiſh heartily (for I loved him as a great <hi>Puritan,</hi> a <hi>ſtrict</hi> and regular <hi>profeſſor)</hi> he may out-live this <hi>diſcracie,</hi> that is at preſent fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and be <hi>more uſeful</hi> to the Church of God <hi>then thus</hi> Yet to ſee and pitty the <hi>diſcompoſure</hi> of Spirit that he is under; hear the man talk a little, and obſerve his ſtrange kind of <hi>unreaſonable reaſonings;</hi> and remember what the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Dead Flyes cauſe</hi> the <hi>oyntmen of the Apothecarie to ſend forth a ſtinking ſavor, ſo doth a lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle folly him that is in reputation for wiſdom and honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118915:11"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. <hi>M. Prynne ſaith,</hi> this poſition of ſome (That <hi>to deliver the Lords Supper, to ſuch as have no pre-exiſtent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace and faith within them, is but to ſet a ſeal to a which cannot work any ſaving grace, and converſion in them.)</hi> This poſition he ſaith is as <hi>falſe,</hi> as God is <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> underſtand no more of the <hi>Truth</hi> of GOD then thus? where is <hi>non ſence in Divinity,</hi> and what is <hi>an impious Paradox</hi> (Mr. <hi>Prynnes</hi> words) if this be not? Let him no more talk of <hi>untheological, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt blaſphemous aſſertions;</hi> except he will juſtifie the <hi>madneſs</hi> (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> calls it) of <hi>Marcion</hi> and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that affirmed there were <hi>two Principles at firſt,</hi> or two beginning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>of good and evil, that were equally poiſed:</hi> Elſe I hope Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> will (as the <hi>diſtemper wears off)</hi> return to his former <hi>right mind.</hi> And that he will live to affirm the great and glorious <hi>Truth</hi> of GOD, to bee <hi>truer,</hi> then the miſtake of any weak and ſinful man can be <hi>falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. But that which aggravateth the matter is this, That what Mr. <hi>Prynne ſaith, is as falſe as God is true.</hi> Is indeed a very truth, <hi>according to God, an undeniable, ſerious, holy truth.</hi> Yet this muſt bear Mr. <hi>Prynnes brand,</hi> for an infinite, unſpeakable, incomprehenſible falſhood; <hi>as falſe</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>as God is true!</hi> This I ſuppoſe is ignorant, bold, and falſe enough! And yet, brethren, this <hi>bold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmer</hi> (of, alas, he knows not what (for I am angry at ſuch <hi>palpable ſtuffe)</hi> takes upon him to <hi>adjure us</hi> to acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in his conceits, and follow his <hi>adviſe</hi> and <hi>fancy,</hi> in no leſſe matters then <hi>(in tremendis myſteriis)</hi> in the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging and adminiſtring the Lords Supper.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> give counſel in the Law with an <hi>honeſt mind,</hi> and good <hi>ſucceſſe,</hi> (wherein they ſay he hath <hi>good skill:)</hi> but God forbid we ſhould no better underſtand our <hi>Theological</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118915:12"/> 
               <hi>work,</hi> then to take our <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> and <hi>precepts</hi> anew from him, that (though never ſo learned in his own) is but very <hi>jejune</hi> and <hi>empty,</hi> as to theſe great and holy things of our <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> and is therein but like him that <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 7. <hi>maketh himſelf rich, and hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his ſeventh <hi>page</hi> he gives a very mean anſwer to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>poſition,</hi> that he cavils at, <hi>(viz.</hi> That <hi>Sacramental Seals ſerve onely to confirm pre-exiſtent, not convey non-exiſtent grace.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he quarrels at, and miſcalleth it a <hi>groſſe Soleciſme in Divinity and Law:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corrigit, magnificat, &amp; neſcit quid ſignificat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To confute the Poſition, he tells us the <hi>primary,</hi> p. 8. <hi>original, moſt uſual end of Seals, and ſealed writings, is to convey and transfer new rights, titles, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>their ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary end to confirm, corroborate, &amp; enlarge eſtates formerly conveyed.</hi> How ſhal Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> teach us in our Profeſſion, that <hi>falls ſhort</hi> in his own? For doth not experience teach us, (and do not as wiſe Counſellors affirm) that the Seal and Writings are <hi>matters of Record,</hi> that of themſelves <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi> convey nothing, but are a laſting <hi>memorial</hi> of what was <hi>bargained, demiſed, purpoſed,</hi> and <hi>conveyed</hi> (and on what terms) before. 'Tis the <hi>act</hi> and <hi>deed</hi> of the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> concerned and agreed before, that is the <hi>conveyance.</hi> And if it cannot be proved that there was no <hi>perſonal actual conveyance,</hi> (as well as a Seal and a Writing) Mr. <hi>Prynne himſelf</hi> (for a ſmall fee) will give it <hi>for Law,</hi> that ſuch a <hi>Writing and Seal</hi> is little better then a <hi>blank,</hi> and ſignifies <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It makes me ſmile to hear him <hi>Romance it ſo gallantly,</hi> in p. 14. and 15. where he relates how the <hi>three Knights,</hi> Mr. <hi>Maurice,</hi> Mr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> and <hi>himſelf,</hi> kill'd the <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118915:12"/> that ſtill <hi>liveth.</hi> At leaſt he ſhews you the <hi>ropes of ſand</hi> where with they <hi>bound him, thus.</hi> Saith Mr. <hi>Prynne, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe preaching and hearing may ſometimes work damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet doth ſometimes work and convey (by the concurrence of Gods Spirit) faith, grace, and repentance: ſo doth the Lords Supper likewiſe; as he ſaith he ſhall prove anon,</hi> or to morrow, or never.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> retains and conſtrains thirty or forty Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to bear up the <hi>bedabbled train</hi> of this vaporing <hi>conceit;</hi> but to prove it indeed, I find not a word <hi>in his Book,</hi> nor is there a word for it in <hi>the Bible.</hi> But we are commanded to preach, and teach, to rebuke, exhort, &amp;c. and by ſuch means, (and by walking like lights, &amp;c.) to indeavour the converſion of the Unregenerate. And for this we have <hi>evidence</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> and abundant witneſs in the <hi>conſcience</hi> of many, bleſſed be the Lord. But for Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> conceit, (and his fellows) <hi>of a proper work of Converſion by the Sacrament,</hi> (for all the rich flouriſhing applauſe that their own mouths give it) it is but but a <hi>fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bankrupt conceit.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 17. he offers to compound at <hi>half a crown</hi> in the pound, with a <hi>Why ſhould they not conſtantly, and frequently adminiſter the Lords Supper to them (viz.</hi> the Unconverted) <hi>becauſe ſome of them may poſſibly, may probably be converted, really reclaimed from their ſins, renued, ſaved by it.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 18, and 19, hee followeth the ſame importunity, <hi>Poſſibly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſome may be converted by it:</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 24 he ſaith, <hi>'Tis uſually and properly wrought by the Lords Supper.</hi> And (if he hath not <hi>proper proof</hi> for it, there is none in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Bible,</hi> for he) <hi>proves</hi> it from the <hi>Queen of Sheba,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 6. and ſome like <hi>inſtances,</hi> and no leſſe (nor more) <hi>pertinent.</hi> And (he after all) from the <hi>weight</hi> of his <hi>bare word</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it upon our <hi>conſciences</hi> (from a <hi>ſingle inſtance,</hi> far fetcht
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118915:13"/> from the <hi>Weſt of England,</hi> with a confident <hi>aſſumption</hi> thereupon, that <hi>ſome,</hi> nay <hi>many</hi> have been converted by the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw</hi> We anſwer, What God hath done of his <hi>meer grace of prerogative,</hi> is not the matter in queſtion: but we are to <hi>regard</hi> what is in our <hi>Charge and Commiſſion:</hi> where we have no <hi>command nor leave,</hi> that I know, to adminiſter the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> according to Mr. <hi>Prynnes Inſtitution.</hi> What if the Lord Chriſt were pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a Thief mercy upon the Croſſe, may we therefore admit of <hi>Thievs</hi> to the <hi>Lord's Table?</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> tells us, (in his ſounder times and Writings) of two <hi>Mimicks, or Stage-plaiers</hi> converted, whilſt they were blaſphemouſly diſhonouring Chriſt in their ridiculous and Mimical act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adminiſtring the <hi>Sacrament of Baptiſme:</hi> (I mean <hi>Porphyrius</hi> and <hi>Arddion;)</hi> Would therefore Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> if he were a <hi>Miniſter</hi> himſelf (that can lay ſuch a <hi>heavy burthen</hi> upon us) admit him to the <hi>Lord's Table,</hi> that had lately committed but a <hi>Mimical rape,</hi> or acted the <hi>Divel upon a Stage?</hi> If nay; then Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> is ours. If yea; What meant Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> to <hi>make</hi> (or my ſelf and others to buy at ſo dear a rate,) that <hi>ſeven ſtringed whip</hi> (a book of great <hi>reading,</hi> and then, of as great <hi>zeal)</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Hiſtriomaſtix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath not Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> heard of that <hi>famous Cook</hi> (in the Church-hiſtory) that was converted by beholding the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>flame,</hi> and feeling the <hi>heat of his fire:</hi> hath he not heard of <hi>ſome,</hi> that were converted by the <hi>receit of an alms,</hi> (why will he not then be as bountifull of his <hi>own,</hi> as hee would have us be of <hi>Gods Table?</hi> Hath no Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> heard, that <hi>juſt Suſpenſion</hi> hath had it's <hi>numbers of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts?</hi> If not, I could tell of <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>plentiful experience</hi> that way. And if the worthy Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> (as once I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118915:13"/> thought him) were under my Miniſtry; I ſhould try the experiment (if he ſhould obtrude) upon <hi>himſelf,</hi> (for all his <hi>Law-tricks)</hi> (as I have ſucceſsfully and moſt happily done upon others.) And <hi>rejoyce not that he were made ſorry, but that he might be ſorrowfull to repentance; that he might be made ſorry after a Godly manner, that he might not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv damage in any thing.</hi> For the ſin of the man is <hi>very great;</hi> and his book <hi>very ſinfull,</hi> (the <hi>Rubrick</hi> it ſelf being <hi>judg;)</hi> and for my ſo doing I ſhould not be afraid to refer the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to GOD, and the judgment of a <hi>nationall Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pryn.</hi> Pag. 3. he objecteth, <hi>the Lords Supper is no where called a ſeal in Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What if it be not called a ſeal in <hi>expreſſe words</hi> of <hi>Scripture:</hi> is it therefore <hi>no ſeal?</hi> what we find a ſeal and a ſealing Ordinance <hi>in the effect,</hi> is ſo in truth, though we find it <hi>not named</hi> (nor our own names) in Scripture. That which hath a power of witneſs <hi>to evidence &amp; confirm is a ſeal,</hi> without <hi>exception;</hi> ſo the blood of the <hi>paſſeover</hi> was <hi>a ſeal</hi> of the <hi>promiſed ſafety &amp; protection</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> being <hi>ſprinckled on the ſide poſts and lintel of their doors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> confeſſeth <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>that circumciſion was a ſeal,</hi> if ſo; was it a <hi>ſeal</hi> as a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> or onely under ſome other <hi>conſideration?</hi> if the <hi>latter,</hi> what was the <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> if the <hi>former,</hi> why ſhould not that which was <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to one <hi>Sacrament</hi> be common to the other?</p>
            <p>3. Is an impreſſion upon the <hi>ſhamefull part of the body a ſeal,</hi> and is not an <hi>impreſſion</hi> upon the ſanctified <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>ſoul</hi> of a believer a <hi>Seal?</hi> nay doth not the very face of a holy <hi>Communicant,</hi> bear <hi>a ſeal</hi> of a holy refreſhing <hi>cheerfulneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. The <hi>Lords Supper</hi> doth alſo <hi>confirm,</hi> and therefore (Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> being judg) it is a <hi>ſeal: (if but ſecondarily, pag.</hi> 8.) and ſo are all the <hi>inſtances</hi> by him mentioned, <hi>in a ſort.</hi> But there is no need that every thing that <hi>ſealeth onely</hi> ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118915:14"/> 
               <hi>confirm,</hi> nor every thing that <hi>confirmeth</hi> be a <hi>ſeal properly;</hi> but the <hi>Sacrament</hi> doth both <hi>ſeal,</hi> and <hi>confirm</hi> the <hi>believer</hi> that receiveth <hi>in faith,</hi> and therefore is <hi>a ſeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. M. <hi>Prynne</hi> confeſſeth <hi>an immateriall and inviſible ſeal,</hi> ſet on the <hi>ſoul or fore-head, by the Spirit of God</hi> or his <hi>Angels. pag.</hi> 5. I hope then to ſay <hi>Sacraments,</hi> or <hi>Seals.</hi> may be as tollerable, as to ſay <hi>ſoul or fore-head;</hi> for where doth M. <hi>Prynne</hi> find them put one for the other, or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells</hi> for the <hi>Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. What abſurdity will follow, if we ſay, that in the <hi>Communion</hi> God doth <hi>annoint us,</hi> and <hi>ſeal us,</hi> and give us the <hi>earneſt of his ſpirit?</hi> I hope ſome of us have <hi>found it ſo.</hi> And though M. <hi>Pryn</hi> knows not (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the <hi>preſent, for his neutralizing</hi> in this lamentable faſhion,) whoſe <hi>image</hi> and <hi>ſuperſcription</hi> is <hi>ſealed</hi> upon the believing <hi>ſoul,</hi> in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> (in a <hi>ſtrict</hi> and moſt <hi>examinate</hi> manner:) yet there are many humble poor <hi>Saints</hi> of God, that <hi>do know,</hi> and can <hi>ſay and affirm,</hi> that their <hi>feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> at the <hi>Lords Table</hi> leavs a <hi>ſeal indelible</hi> upon their hearts.</p>
            <p>7. After all M. <hi>Prynn's</hi> cavilling at the word <hi>Seal,</hi> and the <hi>materiality,</hi> &amp; <hi>immateriality, properneſs and improper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it,</hi> he granteth the <hi>Lords Supper to be a ſeal,</hi> but not <hi>affixed.</hi> As the <hi>Jews</hi> ſometimes ſaid to <hi>Pilate, write not the King of the Jews, but that he ſaid, I am the King of the Jews:</hi> ſo M. <hi>Prynne</hi> to <hi>extenuate,</hi> what may be, and <hi>diminiſh</hi> from the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>ordinance,</hi> (though he muſt call it a <hi>ſeal,</hi> yet) will not have it called a <hi>ſeal affixed.</hi> Doth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf know, a <hi>ſeal is not a ſeal</hi> otherwiſe <hi>then affixed?</hi> and yet he hath the audacity to call this <hi>a falſe, improper, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural paradox, pag</hi> 7. &amp; for proof refers you to another <hi>pretty piece</hi> of his, that (like the <hi>ſhepherds Calender)</hi> will perhaps refer you to this again.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118915:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Pryn.</hi> Pag. 25. M. <hi>Prynne</hi> confeſſes <hi>a competent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and hiſtoricall belief at leaſt, of the death, paſſion, and merits of Chriſt, and of the matter, and ends of the Lords Supper, are pre-required of all ſuch who are admitted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,</hi> &amp; pag 34. <hi>the Communicants must be worthy,</hi> &amp; pag 26. <hi>there muſt be an externall profeſſion of the Goſpel.</hi> And then he gravely concludeth, <hi>it muſt therefore now be duly adminiſtred to all unregenerate Chriſtians, as a converting Ordinance,</hi> and pag. 39 <hi>Whether regenerate, or unregenerate, ignorant or knowing, ſcandalous or unblameable.</hi> Is this good ſence in divinity ſweet M. <hi>Prynne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pryn.</hi> Pag. 37. You have <hi>more</hi> to as good <hi>ſence</hi> and purpoſe, <hi>at large,</hi> that <hi>becauſe the Lords Supper is part of the Ministers office, as well as preaching, therefore it is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a faith-begetting ſoul-converting ordinance.</hi> and pag. 42. in proſecution, he tells us in brief, <hi>there is not any means or motive to faith or converſion, in the Goſpell preached, which is not included</hi> in the Lords Supper. <hi>Therefore ſaith he (is't not a good inference? our oppoſites must either grant the Lords ſupper a ſoul-converting, grace-begetting ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as well as Preaching, or elſe diſclaim preaching to be ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We will not <hi>ſtrike</hi> him when <hi>hee's down,</hi> hee hath ſo pittfully <hi>foyled himſelfe,</hi> that 'tis no <hi>glory</hi> at all to <hi>confute</hi> that that is all <hi>confuſion</hi> (but no non-ſence I pray in it's <hi>parts</hi> &amp; <hi>principles.</hi> 'Tis enough that he ſees what his deep <hi>reaſoning</hi> amounteth to in all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pryn.</hi> Pag. 35 and 38 M. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſaith, <hi>in the Sacrament all is moſt lovely held forth to eyes and ears, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be a ſoul-converting Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is not this <hi>ſound reaſoning?</hi> alas how blindly doth M. <hi>Pryn</hi> ſpeak of <hi>eys and ears;</hi> doth he not know that <hi>unregenerate</hi> perſons have neither <hi>eyes,</hi> nor <hi>ears,</hi> nor <hi>taſte,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118915:15"/> but their very <hi>minds and conſciences are defiled?</hi> Though he pleaſeth to ſpend ſome waſte leavs, <hi>pag.</hi> 45 to tell us <hi>that ſight is better then hearing,</hi> yet to <hi>his</hi> and <hi>our</hi> buſineſs in hand 'tis to <hi>no purpoſe;</hi> for he knows every thing is received <hi>(ad modum recipientis)</hi> according to the <hi>capacity</hi> of the <hi>receiver.</hi> The <hi>Cock</hi> in the <hi>fable</hi> might have <hi>taught</hi> him ſo, and we ſee <hi>bruit beaſts</hi> are not <hi>affected,</hi> with what they <hi>ſee</hi> out of their <hi>proper element;</hi> neither is the <hi>Brutiſh man affected,</hi> nor doth the <hi>the carnall man either diſcern,</hi> or <hi>receive the things of God; becauſe they are fooliſhneſſe to him, and becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> The <hi>eye</hi> indeed is a good <hi>witneſſe,</hi> but firſt it muſt be <hi>taught</hi> by the <hi>ear,</hi> the <hi>difference</hi> of things, before it can <hi>judg</hi> of their excellency. Therefore the wiſe man <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 12. affirmeth, that <hi>knowledge comes in by hearing,</hi> and is <hi>after</hi> (and not <hi>firſt)</hi> demonſtrated <hi>by ſight: the hearing ear, and the ſeeing eye is of the Lord.</hi> What needs therefore M. <hi>Prynne</hi> to bring <hi>heaps upon heaps,</hi> to prove <hi>ſeeing</hi> ſuch a glorious <hi>ſence</hi> (as indeed it is to thoſe that have it.) It had been more pertinent for him to have brought <hi>one page,</hi> or ſome <hi>one line,</hi> or one <hi>clear Scripture,</hi> (as he promiſed hee <hi>would anon)</hi> for <hi>proof</hi> and <hi>evidence</hi> to his <hi>propoſition; that the Sacrament is a ſoul-converting, grace begetting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pryn. <hi>Page</hi> 39. He ſaith, <hi>in the Apoſtles times, all viſible Church-members profeſſing Chriſt, made but one myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal bodie of Chriſt. And by and by</hi> ſubjoyns, <hi>whether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> or <hi>unregenerate, ignorant</hi> or <hi>knowing, ſcandalous</hi> or <hi>unblameable, &amp;c.</hi> and 56 <hi>'tis</hi> ſaith he <hi>a converting ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to the unregenerate, inſtructing to the ignorant, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the vicious, comforting to the gracious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I wiſh that M. <hi>Prynne</hi> (or any of his <hi>gang)</hi> would give us but a <hi>Goſpell ſence</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> and the <hi>like</hi> groundleſſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118915:15"/> 
               <hi>expreſſions;</hi> Let him ſhew out of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and good <hi>writers,</hi> his evidence for what he <hi>affirms;</hi> and he <hi>ſhall bore me thorow the ear, and I will be his ſervant for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If all viſible Church-members make one <hi>mystical body of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>unregenerate, ſcandalous</hi> and <hi>ignorant,</hi> are all of that <hi>number;</hi> What then ſhall become of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> antienter and ſound <hi>Doctrine,</hi> of the <hi>perpetuity onely of a regenerate mans eſtate,</hi> and his memberſhip in Chriſt? (a book of his own, that I wiſh Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> would <hi>read over,</hi> that his then <hi>better mind,</hi> might cure his <hi>now later errors).</hi> What ſhall we ſay to the <hi>antient</hi> received <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, Many are in the Church, that are not of the Church.</hi> Nay, what ſhall we ſay to the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>All are not Iſrael, that are of Iſrael?</hi> Is it fit we ſhould leave the <hi>Word of God, and ſerve Tables;</hi> Shall we <hi>renounce</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Doctrine,</hi> and embrace what Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſaith, and onely ſaith, it was practiſed in the Apoſtles time? Let Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſhew us the <hi>practice,</hi> we will ſhew him the <hi>precept of the Apoſtles,</hi> not <hi>ſtrengthened,</hi> but honeſtly <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded</hi> with his <hi>own expoſition.</hi> Let him retract that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he doth <hi>impoſe and peſter</hi> us with his <hi>new jingles</hi> and <hi>conceits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. And whereas Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Sacraments are a converting Ordinance to the unregenerats, inſtructing to the ignorant, reforming to the vitious.</hi> I would intreat him in ſo <hi>weighty</hi> a <hi>matter,</hi> and ſo <hi>unheard of,</hi> wee might have more then his <hi>bare word:</hi> we will not <hi>retort</hi> too bitterly upon him, that <hi>lame Giles his haltings</hi> (that he pretended to cure) are fallen upon <hi>himſelf;</hi> and as <hi>Beza</hi> wittily nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his <hi>Cyclops Heſhuſius,</hi> arguing much at Mr. <hi>Prynnes</hi> rate, about the very <hi>queſtion</hi> in hand, <hi>(quid impii in coena recipiant?) what benefit the wicked receiv in the Supper of the Lord?</hi> who producing a pitifull <hi>argument</hi> for it, (yet
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118915:16"/> as ſufficient as Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> firſt born:) <hi>Beza</hi> I ſay anſwers him, <hi>Dico hanc concluſionem non eſſe crocodilinam, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus aſininam.</hi> Such language were <hi>too broad</hi> to be <hi>Engliſhed,</hi> or <hi>applyed</hi> to Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> (not for <hi>eſteem</hi> that I have to Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> late <hi>arguing,</hi> but) for reſpect that I have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>former</hi> excellent good <hi>deſerts.</hi> Sorry I am <hi>for our ſelvs,</hi> that he ſhould give us <hi>a good Pail of Milk, and kick it down when he hath done!</hi> ſorry I am (more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) for him, that <hi>his works ſhould be burnt up, and he loſe what he hath wrought for, and he himſelf ſaved as by fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I will therefore onely <hi>modeſtly</hi> ask him (as learned <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> inquired of <hi>Dureus:) Quomodo hanc ad alios gratiam derivari intelligimus? how</hi> (good Sir) <hi>ſhall we underſtand the Grace of God to be conveyed by the Sacrament to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unregenerate?</hi> For a learned <hi>Divine (Beza)</hi> gives us this for a <hi>concluſion,</hi> and we have all <hi>received</hi> it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the word of God for truth: <hi>(Indigne ſumere ſacra ſymbola, et rem ipſam per incredulitatem repellere, neceſſario cohaerent: Sicut è contrario haec duo, rite ſumere ſymbola, &amp; rem ipſam fide percipere.) To take the holy elements unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, and to refuſe the thing it ſelf, (in the Sacrament,) must needs go together: ſo on the contrary do theſe two, to take the elements rightly, and to receive the thing it ſelf (in the Sacrament) by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pryn.</hi> Pag. 55, Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> compares our <hi>preparatory work of pre-examination</hi> (of ſo great <hi>uſe, neceſſity</hi> and <hi>continuance in the Church of God)</hi> unto the <hi>conſeſſion unto a popiſh Prieſt; and makes them</hi> (in a canine cenſure), <hi>whelps of the ſame Litter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To his <hi>rage</hi> ſhall I ſay (as <hi>Jacob Gen.</hi> 49. 7. to his <hi>ſons) Curſed be his anger for it was fierce, and his wrath for it was cruel.</hi> Shall I ſay, <hi>his fury be upon his, own head, and his rage periſh with him?</hi> No, no, no; let his <hi>ſin pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118915:16"/> and let him be <hi>reſtored,</hi> and be as a <hi>brand plucked out of the burning.</hi> For if ever it might be ſaid, that <hi>Anger is a ſhort madneſs,</hi> it appears in this 55 page of his, it <hi>words at length.</hi> Indeed (hee's the <hi>beſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> at the <hi>worſt work:)</hi> hee's tranſformed not into a whelp of ſome ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Litter (as he <hi>phraſes it)</hi> of ſome <hi>ſnarling mungrel,</hi> but rampeth like a terrible old <hi>African Lion</hi> roaring and tormented; whoſe <hi>eies</hi> are troubled with <hi>little flies,</hi> and digged out with his own claws. And his <hi>heart</hi> I fear is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as <hi>cruel</hi> as his <hi>hard ſpeeches;</hi> he would <hi>eject and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend,</hi> and play the <hi>Haman</hi> with us. He cannot heat the <hi>furnace of his indignation</hi> hot enough, to ſhew his rage againſt poor <hi>ſhelterleſſe Miniſters,</hi> that will not bow down to the <hi>Idol of his imagination.</hi> But bleſſed be the Lord that hath not delivered us as a <hi>prey</hi> to <hi>his,</hi> and the <hi>teeth of all his furious ones!</hi> I will paſſe by therefore his monſtrous railing, <hi>large</hi> and <hi>long, falſe</hi> and <hi>vehement,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> the curſe of <hi>Shimei;</hi> and ſhake it off, as <hi>Paul</hi> the Viper into the fire: And if he can recover his mind, and ſweeten it a little with the love of <hi>Truth and peace,</hi> I will ſhew him the reaſon and neceſſity of our pre-examination and trial of the grace and fitneſs of thoſe with whom we commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and to whom we diſpenſe the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>2. Firſt for pre-examination therefore though <hi>charity hopeth all things</hi> (1 Cor. 13. 5.) <hi>and believeth all things;</hi> yet (take <hi>Chryſoſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Lyra</hi>'s expoſition as very good) <hi>Charity hopeth onely all that can be hoped (omnia bona) Sit malus licet, adeſt corrigens, proſpiciens, ſtudium impendens,</hi> Chryſoſt. in loc.) Charity corrects and takes pains with the <hi>bad,</hi> as well as care and ſtudie for the <hi>good.</hi> But the other two carry the Text quite away from our Adverſaries, and apply it otherwiſe <hi>(charitas omnia ſperat quae promittuntur, &amp;c.) Charity believs all</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118915:17"/> 
               <hi>the promiſes, ſuffers all that God inflicteth, and expects with patience,</hi> Aquin &amp; Lyr. in loc. The Apoſtle bids us <hi>ſhun</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 16. (nice acuteneſs) <hi>profane and vain babblings,</hi> wrangling, controverting, <hi>for they increaſe to more ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> 'Tis a general <hi>miſchief</hi> that falls upon all the <hi>vain Diſputers</hi> of this world, that they <hi>yoak</hi> not themſelvs to the <hi>Truth;</hi> but ſeek all over to have onely ſome appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of truth on their parts, willing rather to <hi>hide their ſhame,</hi> then to <hi>forſake it.</hi> But he that is of the truth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the light, and is ſound in the Word, and in the Faith, and ſhifteth not to corners, and ſnatches not at quiddities for defence, He holds the <hi>antient deciſions of the Church</hi> thoſe old <hi>Land-marks;</hi> and fears not the plea nor objection of any: for they reſiſt to no more purpoſe, then <hi>Jannes and Jambres reſiſted Moſes: Arons rod</hi> eat up all the <hi>rods</hi> of the <hi>Inchanters,</hi> ſo the clear Word of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the <hi>forme of wholeſome words,</hi> in the <hi>tenents of the Church of God; and the ſtanding doctrine of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel,</hi> will devour all <hi>upſtart falſhoods</hi> and <hi>conceits</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>2. It was the praiſe of the Angel of the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, Rev.</hi> 2. 2. That he was careful to <hi>examine,</hi> and he did <hi>examine, and found ſome liers;</hi> was it a <hi>glory</hi> to him, and is it (as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> calls it) <hi>a ſoul-murthering cruelty</hi> in us? Shall Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> (and his Legion) tell us, <hi>You take too much upon you, you ſons of Levi.</hi> 'Tis but a ſmal matter for us to be judged by them, that have <hi>tongues</hi> longer then their <hi>arms,</hi> that can <hi>judge falſly,</hi> but through divine <hi>reſtraint</hi> cannot <hi>execute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Might (nay muſt) the <hi>Prieſt</hi> in the Law <hi>ſeparate between the clean and the unclean,</hi> and may not the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of the Goſpel do the like in their <hi>ſtations?</hi> no, not where <hi>we ſee the Leproſie in their foreheads?</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118915:17"/> ſaith no; Who ſhall controul his bare word? He tells us the Sacrament is a <hi>reforming Ordinance to the vicious, &amp;c.</hi> (as you have heard before): and he would have us <hi>jurare in verba,</hi> for he doth <hi>adjure</hi> us to his <hi>conceit.</hi> And for the duty of <hi>Examination,</hi> he referrs that to the profane and vicious themſelvs; and therefore he often drops that Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. into the margent, and <hi>preſſeth it</hi> as <hi>none of our duty to examine.</hi> But how if it be, and we neglect it? wil Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> be retained on our part to plead for us; will he anſwer to God for our neglect? I doubt his face will not be hard enough, nor his caſe good enough to ſtand in the judgment.</p>
            <p>You may ſee how thoſe that have a mind to cavil at the Truth, will ſnatch at any thing to ſupport them! The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is but once in all the Scripture tranſlated <hi>to examine,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28, <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> and yet here they all lay hold <hi>(concluſum est contra dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matistas,</hi> O they have enough againſt them, for whom they have no names bad enough.) But ſuppoſe the word had here been tranſlated (as often 'tis) <hi>to like, to allow, to approve (Rom.</hi> 4. 22. 1. 28. 2. 18. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 10. &amp;c.) how would theſe <hi>crackers</hi> have done for an argument, would they have inferred, that they that can <hi>allow, and like, and approve themſelves,</hi> the <hi>Ministry</hi> and <hi>Church of God,</hi> muſt do ſo too? Will not the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate and profane perſon <hi>like,</hi> and <hi>allow,</hi> and <hi>approve</hi> better of him, (and take Mr. <hi>Prynnes</hi> counſel to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident enough) then the moſt tender-hearted repentant, and fit Communicant? But if <hi>perſonal examination</hi> were ſufficient; can a Drunkard, or Unregenerate perſon of the like ſort, <hi>examine himſelf;</hi> where the very <hi>imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is bruitiſh,</hi> and the <hi>mind axd conſcience corrupted and defiled?</hi> Is not a young and ſanctified <hi>child,</hi> better and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118915:18"/> fitter for the Communion, then an old and fooliſh beaſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe words (therefore) <hi>Let a man examine himſelf,</hi> are not to be underſtood <hi>excluſively;</hi> but of the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant care</hi> that is to be had, and <hi>examination and proof of every mans conſcience to himſelf in the ſight of God.</hi> For it often may happen, that a loving, willing, flexible Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, may be too gentle, facile, and indulgent; loath to diſcourage, and forward to admit: but ſet a man be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, and examine himſelf yet more thorowly; and not reſt wholly upon a forreign favourable approbation.</p>
            <p>4. If all Ordinances be granted to be <hi>converting</hi> (as <hi>M. Prynne</hi> aſſerts amongſt heaps of other the like notions) where then doth the Scripture deny it, unto the <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning care of a conſcientious Paſtor,</hi> who is commanded <hi>to know the ſtate of his flock;</hi> and Chriſtians <hi>to ſubmit unto his over-ſight,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. <hi>Obey them that have the rule (or guide) over you, and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for you.</hi> Yet let the Saints of God know in all the Church and Churches of <hi>England,</hi> that this <hi>rule and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,</hi> (is not as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſuggeſteth) to arrogate power to our ſelves, for we profeſſe with the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. <hi>We have not dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy.</hi> Examining Communicants is <hi>ſervice and help,</hi> and not <hi>a dominion:</hi> We <hi>help</hi> the <hi>joy,</hi> and <hi>ſettle</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of a believer; and we <hi>help on the ſorrow, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and converſion</hi> of unbelievers by it.</p>
            <p>5. Doth not the Apoſtle charge us, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28. <hi>To take heed to our ſelves, and to the flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made us over-ſeers:</hi> (A Scripture that Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> doth prepoſterouſly apply, to the mollifying us, towards the adminiſtring to unregenerate perſons, <hi>p.</hi> 18. 57.) what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118915:18"/> manner of duty and care then is incumbent upon us? here (if ever) we may ſay, <hi>Abundans cautela non nocet,</hi> 'tis good to be ſure, to enquire into the fitneſs of all is ſafe; and to do it with an affectionate, tender, and inoffenſive reſpect is civil. I wiſh Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> and his abettors, had read <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. who blameth mens examination of themſelves: <hi>(Non quem ad modum nunc facimus, &amp;c.) Communicants ſhould not ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as now they do; to come to the Lords Table at ſuch or ſuch a ſolemnity, onely as others do; A man must forbear in a Fever from his own table, becauſe of the abundance of his ill-humors</hi> (Longè magis hanc tangere nefas eſt) <hi>much more it is dangerous to come to the Lords Table when abſurd luſts hinder us, that are worſe then a Fever.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtoms</hi> words, which if Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> had well conſidered, he would not (perhaps) ſo far have indulged wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; as to tell them, that the <hi>Lords Supper is converting to the unregenerate, and reforming to the vitious:</hi> nor have <hi>ſnibb'd,</hi> nay almoſt <hi>anathematized</hi> ſerviceable conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Miniſters</hi> for their <hi>examinate care</hi> and <hi>love.</hi> I wiſh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts might convince Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> of his unhappy error! but if not, they muſt yet more fully perſwade us of our duty, not to be careleſs and <hi>remiſſe</hi> in the <hi>rule and overſight that God</hi> hath betruſted unto us. I wonder where M. <hi>Prynne</hi> (and his) would ſet the limits of our Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial vigilancy. Are we <hi>Gods builders,</hi> and may we lay any <hi>rubbiſh</hi> upon his foundation, that is hurried or tumbled thither by the <hi>impulſe of Satan for damnation?</hi> Are we Gods Stewards, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. and give no better account of our truſt, but to give <hi>Loiterers,</hi> (nay <hi>hinderers and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of others)</hi> our <hi>Lords meat, drink,</hi> and <hi>wages?</hi> No, we have learned <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 45, &amp; <hi>Luk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 12. 42. that the <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and wiſe ſervant must give every one</hi> in the houſhold his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118915:19"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his proportion of meat;</hi> (not feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all alike,) and it muſt bee done in ſeaſon; he muſt know when to give, and <hi>what to give.)</hi> The Lord give us that <hi>wiſdome and faithfulneſs,</hi> and the bleſſing that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the next verſe,) <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom his maſter when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. The Apoſtle forewarns us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>Not to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of other mens ſins.</hi> What can be a greater <hi>partaking, (if qui patitur facit, if connivance be a ſin)</hi> then for any of us to <hi>inveigh against ſin in the Pulpit,</hi> &amp; ſullenly refuſe unregenerate wretches, ſwearers, drunkards, &amp;c. at our <hi>own Table,</hi> and to receive them at the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> and there to give them <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> and carve them of the <hi>royall dainties?</hi> Is not this to indulge, and abſolve him in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> whom I have condemned in the Word (and diſclaimed in private converſation?) <hi>ſuch as have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their uncleanneſs</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 21. Gods word ſaith, 1 Cor. 6. 9. <hi>ſuch ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God.</hi> Shall my <hi>words</hi> and <hi>action</hi> witneſs unto him (in Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> language) that he is a <hi>member of Chriſts miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body,</hi> and ſhall I (ſo far as in me lies) give him the <hi>ſeal of the inheritance?</hi> when as if he were to be baptized I ſhould not dare to <hi>baptize him,</hi> God forbid.</p>
            <p>7. If <hi>Miniſters</hi> have indeed a power to admit, it muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently follow they have a power to exclude, or elſe <hi>(Infelix ò patrum, Gen.</hi> 9) unhappy are thoſe <hi>fathers,</hi> that have not the <hi>power of the Rod,</hi> as well as <hi>proviſion of bread,</hi> and a ſpirit of <hi>meekneſs.</hi> But 'tis objected that 'tis too much to be <hi>truſted to one man alone (to ſuſpend from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:)</hi> &amp; I anſwer, 'tis <hi>too much</hi> to be truſted to <hi>one beaſt alone,</hi> to prophane the <hi>Lords Table</hi> at his <hi>bruitiſh pleaſure,</hi> to his own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>8. I ſhall ſhew what herein hath been received as true,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118915:19"/> 
               <hi>Evangelical, Sacramentall doctrine,</hi> by thoſe that have had a name and a pillar in the houſe of GOD. M. <hi>Hooker</hi> in his Eccleſiaſticall pollicy <hi>lib.</hi> 5 <hi>ſect.</hi> 68. <hi>The examination of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants we reject not</hi> (conſenting to learned M. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> therein) <hi>Leſt we admit Popiſh Communicants, whom we ought not to admit in any wiſe, till their Goſpell-like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiviour hath removed all ſuſpition of Popery from them.</hi> And ſaith, (in Cartwrights very words) <hi>he that giveth ſuch the Sacrament, giveth the bread provided for Chilidren unto doggs: and bringeth into the paſture provided for the ſheep, Swine and unclean beaſts; which is contrary to the faith, and truſt, that ought to be in a ſteward of the Lords Houſe. For, the adminiſtration of the Sacraments unto them, is a declaration of Gods favour and reconciliation with them, and a plain preaching; Partly, that they are waſhed already from their ſin, Partly, that they are of the Houſhold of God, and ſuch as the Lord wil feed to eternall life. Which is not to be done unto thoſe, which are not of the houſhold of faith.</hi> Thus far ſaith the <hi>learned man</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>received doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Field lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 22 ſaith, <hi>the guides of the Church have power to puniſh ſin, with ſuſpenſion, excommunication &amp;c. and ſaith, that he, that for his contempt and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is debarred from the uſe of the Sacraments, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly excluded from all acceſſe to the Throne of grace.</hi> He ſaith further <hi>(ibid) and laſtly the power of Miniſters is twofold, they have the key of ſcience and iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. To teach, reprove, govern, and yield ſacramentall aſſurance of Gods mercy, and grace, by diſpenſing the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Chriſt hath inſtituted.</hi> So far affirmeth that <hi>worthy man</hi> all in one <hi>chap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Randall</hi> (in <hi>his Tract, upon the Sacrament)</hi> layes a great charge upon us, <hi>to be choiſe and wary, whom</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118915:20"/> 
               <hi>we admit to the Lords Table. Biſhop Bilſon (pag.</hi> 222) uſeth an apt ſimilitude, <hi>If the Guard keep out an noble man from the pallace upon command, are they therefore above the nobles? and if a paſtor turns one from the Communion, he is not therefore above him?</hi> Laſtly (for I am not for <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> but <hi>weight</hi> of proofs unto what I do affirm (Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (now flouriſhing, whom I love and honor (not for his <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> but) for his <hi>zeal, activity,</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> in our work,) makes a fair overture to them that will be <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants; Perform your duty, ſo far as is antecedent to mine, and I muſt offer you the Sacraments: but if you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to repent, and believ, and profeſſe ſo, in a credible ſort; or in will, or life, profeſs you do not ſo, and yet demand the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you do not your duty, and ſo I am not obliged.</hi> So far M. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Diſputation <hi>fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe evidences are enough, yet if Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> and the reſt be not ſatisfied, let them read the 83 <hi>Homily</hi> of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon <hi>Matth.</hi> at theſe words, <hi>Ad vos qui mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratis dicta volo, &amp;c.</hi> I ſpeak to you that adminiſter; <hi>Let no cruel, unmerciful, impure wretch be admitted; nay, though a Captain, a Conſul, nay an Emperour ſhould come, &amp;c.</hi> And a little nearer the end <hi>(dico horribile) I tell you (ſaith he) a very dreadful thing, it is not ſo bad to have thoſe that are poſſeſſed by the Divel there with us.</hi> Omnes igitur, &amp;c. <hi>Let us therefore in ſimplicity drive away all, whom we ſee to come unworthily; and if any ſuch of boldneſs, or mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will indeed come to the Table; fear him not, reject him, fear not man but God: for if thou fear man, they will deride thee; but if God, they will honor thee. And if thou darest not do this, tell me, and I will do it: and part with my life rather, &amp;c.</hi> And ſuch was the zeal and ſtedfaſtneſs of the <hi>golden-tongued</hi> and <hi>ſteel-hearted Chryſoſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly for the concluſion of this little work; becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118915:20"/> Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> talketh ſo high of the <hi>Apoſtles times, Councils, Fathers, Church-Liturgies, and Proteſtant-writers:</hi> and yet we ſee no good authoritie, whereupon his conceit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conceit doth lean: we will conſider of his oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And though we cannot in ſo ſmall a work (intended onely for <hi>admonition,</hi> and to expreſſe our <hi>juſt diſlike</hi> of his <hi>inſolencies, and groundleſs and dangerous aſſertions)</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate our ſelves to the <hi>Fathers, and Councils, and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church-hiſtories;</hi> for I muſt conſider my ſtrength and intention. And though as for <hi>Alexander Hales, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure, Bellarmine</hi> and the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> (which are all four-footed, and full cry after Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s game) I count them not worth the pains upon this queſtion; neither is their Authority deſerving ſo high a commendation as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> gives them, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <hi>more clear then the light</hi> (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily but the light of <hi>Gloworms,</hi> and <hi>rotten chips:</hi> yet to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all) to Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> their light hath unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved <hi>(Objectum nimium ſenſibile, deſtruens ſenſum)</hi> an occaſion of conferring, or confirming him under inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable darkneſs, for which I heartily lament and pity him!</p>
            <p>Yet as to our <hi>Church-Liturgies, Canons, and Proteſtant Writers,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak ſomewhat that will exceedingly <hi>diſcountenance</hi> and <hi>rebuke</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s conceit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I know well that Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> (next to Mr. <hi>John Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> of <hi>Coleman ſtreet)</hi> is old excellent at <hi>ſnipping</hi> a piece out of ſome <hi>new cloth</hi> (ſome excellent Author) to <hi>patch</hi> an <hi>old ragged ſrippery,</hi> that was worn quite <hi>thred-bare</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was born: And I could give ſome inſtances for the purpoſe, but I have not leiſure; and beſides, any learned men, that conſult his dealings elſwhere, may ſee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118915:21"/> without my ſpectacles, how like a <hi>Hanun</hi> he hath uſed his miſerable quotations.</p>
            <p>The few evidences therefore that I produce ſhall bee <hi>plain,</hi> and <hi>full,</hi> and <hi>clear to the purpoſe;</hi> without any <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint</hi> or <hi>conſtraint</hi> any way, but ſhall take them in their native proper intention. And for brevity, and to ſpare tranſcriptions in <hi>Latine,</hi> and into <hi>Engliſh both,</hi> you ſhall have them (a few of many hundreds) truly quoted, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred,</hi> and <hi>tranſlated</hi> where need is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Church Liturgie</hi> it was ſevere enough, if <hi>Miniſters</hi> would have uſed it (as ſome in the worſt times did) in the right and full power of it. <hi>If any of thoſe (who have ſignified the names to their Curate) be an open and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious evill liver, ſo that the Congregation by him is offended &amp;c. the Curate ſhall call him, and advertiſe him, not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come to the Lords Table, untill &amp;c</hi> (and further) <hi>the Curate ſhall not ſuffer thoſe, betwixt whom he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth malice and hatred to reign, to be partakers of the Lords Table.</hi> And (in the concluſion) <hi>he ſhall admit the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent perſon, &amp; not him that is obſtinate.</hi> In the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation the Curate ſhall ſay, <hi>If any of you be a blaſphemer of God a hinderer or ſlanderer of his Word, an adulterer, or be in malice, or any other grievious crime; bewail your ſin, and come not to his holy Table, &amp;c.</hi> ſee the order for adminiſtration of the Lords Supper at large.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Canons</hi> were <hi>expreſſe</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> that <hi>no notorious offender, Schiſmatick,</hi> or <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhould be admitted to the Lords Supper.</hi> See Canon. 26, 27, and 28.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For Proteſtant writers, Peter Martyr,</hi> and many others do frequently quote that place in <hi>Aug. de civit. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>(Nec iſti ergo dicendi ſunt manducare corput</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118915:21"/> 
               <hi>Christi, &amp;c.) they are not to be ſaid to eat the body of Chriſt, for they are not to be counted for members of Chriſt, that I may ſay no more, they cannot at once be the members of Chriſt, and members of a harlot, &amp;c.</hi> Yet M. <hi>Prynne</hi> ſaith pag. 39. <hi>they are one myſtical body of Chriſt.</hi> If <hi>Auſtin</hi> were now in conteſt with him, as once with <hi>Petilian;</hi> he muſt ſay it over again, <hi>Prinnus ait, ego nego, cui voltis creda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Peter Martyr in Tract. de Euchar.</hi> makes uſe of a compariſon out of <hi>Cyril,</hi> (that believing Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants are the members of Chriſt) <hi>from wax, that is melted and mixed with other wax:</hi> and ſtrengthens it, with that of <hi>Paul to the Epheſians</hi> 5. 30. <hi>we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones: where Paul underſtands not ſimple fleſh, but cleanſed from ſin, and capable of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and immortality, which the faithfull (though they have it not of their own, nor extracted from Adam) yetclaim of Chriſt, in as much as they are incorporated with him, by the Sacraments, and faith: for there is a coming of Christ upon, &amp; a ſpiritual touch, which Paul well conſidered; when he ſaid to the Galatians, I live, but now not I, but Chriſt liveth in me.</hi> This in his tractate upon the <hi>Euchar.</hi> towards the end written 1549.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> further proveth, that the <hi>unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate receiveth not</hi> (that which Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> affirmeth from <hi>John</hi> 6.) <hi>the body of Chriſt, or fleſh of Chriſt. Nemo enim indigne manducat corpus Chriſti,</hi> for (ſaith he) <hi>the body, or fleſh of Chriſt cannot be received vnworthily by any.</hi> (in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with Doctor <hi>Cheadzey May</hi> 29.)</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> argument might ſtand, (that the <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> or <hi>unregenerate</hi> are properly, and ordinarily converted by the <hi>Lords Supper:</hi> then <hi>Peter Martyr's</hi> argument againſt <hi>Popiſh Tranſubſtantiation</hi> muſt fall to the ground. And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118915:22"/> then Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> hath at leaſt gratified ſome body.</p>
            <p>I know (ſaith this ſame <hi>learned Proteſtant upon</hi> 1 Cor. 1.) <q>that ſuch a <hi>falſhood</hi> goes for currant, that wicked men are the members of Chriſt, but dead, which may be made alive: 'tis as true as thou ſhouldeſt ſay, a dead man is a man. We confeſſe Chriſt can reſtore them to life, by his holy ſpirit, but whilſt that is not done, we cannot grant them to be the members of Chriſt; (neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> grant M. <hi>Prynn's</hi> aſſertion <hi>pag.</hi> 39 that all viſible Church members (regenerate or unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate &amp;c.) make but one myſticall body of Chriſt.) and upon <hi>cap.</hi> 11. See ſaith he, how <hi>Austin</hi> ſhewes, that <hi>they that live wickedly are not of the body</hi> of Chriſt and have <hi>no ſalvation by him,</hi> but thoſe eat the Lord that abide in him, which Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, and wicked Catholicks do not, &amp;c. and upon <hi>cap.</hi> 12. 12. after many expreſſions to the purpoſe, it is evident, that wicked men are truly <hi>not</hi> of the Church, for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>not</hi> life from Chriſt, they may indeed converſe in the Church, but they are not of the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon 1 Cor. Chap. 4. 1. <hi>The Miniſter (the ſteward) ſhould take care, thoſe that live wickedly, he ſhould ſhut them out of the family: and when they be penitent, receive them again.</hi> And (a little after) <hi>Let him not withdraw from looking into thoſe, to whom he ought to distribute the Sacraments; that if he ſee they be doggs, he may drive them away; but if they be pious, and fearing God, he may invite them, and compell them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon 1 Cor. 11. 29. <hi>Furthermore in the Sacraments there are two things, the Word, and the Signs; when as the Word of it ſelf cannot move the hearers deſtitute of faith, and of the Spirit of God; much leſſe can theſe ſigns do it,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118915:22"/> 
               <hi>which if they be compared with the Word, are not ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buoer</hi> (in his ſecond book to <hi>Latomus</hi> blames thoſe <hi>Miſſificks</hi> and <hi>Shavelins,</hi> that they would, contrary to the antient cuſtome of the <hi>Church,</hi> and duty of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> proſtitute the <hi>Sacrament</hi> even to any, though they had <hi>no faith,</hi> nor were no <hi>lively members of Chriſt.</hi> And this (ſaith that worthy man) <hi>(in cauſa eſt cur ita placent, &amp;c)</hi> is the reaſon that falſe worſhip doth ſo pleaſe men; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe howſoever wickedly they live, and ruſh unto all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, yet they ſhall be promiſed mercy from God,</hi> ſee cap. 35, 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Saith <hi>Luther</hi> upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>Doctor in Eccleſia libere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendat quae cum ſcandalo fiant, &amp; impenitentes arceat à communione:</hi> Let the Teacher in the Church freely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſcandals, and drive away impenitent perſons from the Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chemnitius</hi> (in his <hi>Exam. of the Trent Council, de effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia &amp; uſu Sacramenti).</hi> 'Tis (ſaith he) <hi>Luthers</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, in his book <hi>De captiv. Babylon; Omnia Sacramenta ad ſidem alendam inſtituta eſſe.</hi> And <hi>Luther</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, required Faith altogether to the uſe of the Sacrament.</hi> And further in the Examination of the ſeventh Canon (after a large ſpeech to this ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he goeth on in theſe words: <q>Neither is the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the Sacraments ſuch, as if God did infuſe and imprint grace by them to ſalvation, even to them that neither believe, nor accept; as ſome think, and did in former times, as <hi>Aug.</hi> tells, <hi>lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de civit. cap.</hi> 25. and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, The Goſpel is the power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to every one that believeth, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. the word profited them not, not being mixed with faith; So it may be ſaid of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> thoſe viſible words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118915:23"/> 
                  <hi>Seals</hi> of the promiſes.</q> See the reſt as it follows in the whole paragraph.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza</hi> is very copious againſt Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> conceit, all over his Writings, <hi>(De re Sacramentaria, ſub titulo</hi> 13) <hi>Quid ſumunt infideles?</hi> all may there read at large. <hi>Os autem fidei quoniam ſoli fideles afferunt, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Becauſe onely Believers have the mouth of faith, therefore they one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take the very thing (or ſubſtance) it ſelf, and thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth eternal life. But unbelievers eat and drink judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to themſelves, becauſe they diſcern not, that is, deſpiſe and reject the body of the Lord offered, and have no underſtanding of it. Therefore their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation comes, by reaſon, not of the body and blood of Chriſt unworthily taken; (for whereas they are onely taken by faith, they are never taken unworthily, but are quickning:) but of the Body and Blood of Chriſt rejected, and contemned. For the Bread and the Wine muſt not be conſidered as meer Bread and Wine in this action, but as Symbols of the body and blood of our Lord; hence therefore it is, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> See the whole, and what he fully anſwers to ſome like Propoſitions, made by a Student in Divinity, in his 20 Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iunius (de Sacramentis in genere, &amp; de Coena)</hi> hath much that might be tranſcribed; but read onely at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Theſ.</hi> 27. <hi>(In hoc tantum differunt Verbum &amp; Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, &amp;c.) The Word and the Sacrament have this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference;</hi> That <hi>kindles faith.</hi> this <hi>nouriſheth;</hi> that <hi>is like the Charter, this the Seal; that is offered to all, (and is needful to the Sacrament) this not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>POLANUS <hi>(de ſubjectis Coenae Dominicae,</hi> lib. 6. cap. 56.) after a large diſcourſe worth the peruſal, he laies down many ſorts of perſons <hi>not fit to be admitted;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, <hi>impenitent, unbelievers, and ſcandalous, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118915:23"/> 
               <hi>rebellious to Superiors, covetous, Brawlers, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, unclean perſons, thievs, uſurers, drunkards,</hi> have their number: <hi>ſuch are not to be reputed members of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither are any to be admitted, except firſt the Paſtor of the Church hath tried them, that they hold and profeſſe the true doctrine of Faith, &amp;c.</hi> read the reſt at leiſure, <hi>'tis all of the ſame ſtamp,</hi> I ſnip no patches here and there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zach. Vrſine</hi> aboundeth in teſtimony on our part, againſt Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> and his Adherents. <hi>De Sacramentis cum Paulo ac totâ veteri Eccleſiâ:</hi> 
               <q>We profeſſe with <hi>Paul,</hi> and the whole antient Church, that thoſe that are not the living members of Chriſt, do not eat Chriſt. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 10. &amp; 11. The Miniſters ought to admit all to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, whom confeſſion, and life, and the divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution doth not exclude: but on the other ſide they profane the Sacraments, if knowingly they give to thoſe, by whoſe confeſſion, or manners, it is not manifeſt that they are lively members of the Church, or cannot keep the form of the Inſtitution. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 20. The Sacraments are Seals of grace, they are Seals to the Word, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 37. Seals of mutual obligation between God and us. They do not confer grace &amp; its gifts, but they ſeal what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 42. They injure the divine truth, which would communicate the things ſignified (in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to wicked men, which God doth plainly affirm, in all the Scripture, he doth beſtow them onely upon believers. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 48. <hi>See alſo his Exercitations</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>from</hi> 1. <hi>to</hi> 15.) To thoſe that want Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the Sacraments are no Seals of grace, but aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of puniſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </q> By theſe, and many the like, Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> (and <hi>his drifters)</hi> may ſee how far they differ from this excellent Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forbeſius, (Inſtit. Hiſt. Theol. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) calls
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118915:24"/> the Sacrament <hi>(foederis divini Sigillum,</hi> &amp;c. The ſeal of God's Covenant, and the ſeal of Grace purchaſed by Chriſt. And <hi>(Lib.</hi> 11. 7. 9.) <hi>Non per uſum, ſed in uſu, &amp;c.</hi> The true Sacrament doth not exiſt by the uſe, but in the uſe; not by the uſe, as an efficient cauſe; but in the uſe, as in an action neceſſary, by reaſon of the divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius Praetorius</hi> expreſſeth himſelf <hi>(In Homiliis de Coena, pag.</hi> 248.) <hi>Vana eſt queſtio, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis but a vain queſtion, whether the wicked and unbelieving eat the Lords body, when the very Symbols of it belong not to them: and 'tis as impoſſible that they ſhould eat the fleſh of Chriſt, as for a monſter without eie, hand, or mouth, to ſee, take, or eat. <hi>And there further,</hi> The Sacraments are ſeals of the promiſes and Covenant of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man ought to uſe them, but ſuch as find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Covenant, and believe the promiſes of God, <hi>pag.</hi> 246.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſtinguis (in his Catachiſme queſt.</hi> 82,) puts the queſtion, <q>May they be admitted to the Supper, that declare by their life, that they are unbelievers or ungodly? No, in no wiſe: for by that means the Covenant of God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, &amp;c. (and by and by in the <hi>Explic.</hi> ſaith he) if they provoke the wrath of God, who without examining themſelvs do come to the holy Supper, how much more ſhall God be provoked to wrath, if the Church it ſelfe do wink at ſuch groſſe ſins, in thoſe that receive. Which (ſaith he) being ſo; if they do offer themſelvs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the reſt of the members of the Church, it ſhall be the duty of the <hi>Paſtors</hi> to uſe <hi>the keys, given by Chriſt too that end,</hi> and by the Authority of them to <hi>bar</hi> ſuch men from the Supper, till there appear in them Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of repentance, and change of life. (This is not like Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> Doctrine.)</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118915:24"/>
            <p> GERHARD <hi>(In Loc. Com. de coena, cap.</hi> 20. <hi>numb.</hi> 215) enters a vaſte and learned diſſent from Mr. <hi>Prynne. Num noſtra ſententia eſt?</hi> 
               <q>What <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> do we ſay, that in the Euchariſt thoſe that continue in ſins, and perſevere in them againſt conſcience, and retain a purpoſe of ſin, nor bring the fear of God, nor repentance, do receive remiſſion of ſins? No verily: but we teach in expreſſe words, that impenitent ones, and ſuch as continue in their ſins againſt conſcience, eat and drink judgment to themſelvs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>cap.</hi> 21 <hi>Numb.</hi> 223. hee's larger yet, (but 'tis worth the reading even of Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> himſelf) <hi>Notorii peccatores</hi> &amp;c. <q>Notorious ſinners, which obſtinately continue in their ſins and wickedneſs, againſt their conſciences, nor give any evidence of repentance, ſuch are not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the holy Supper. <hi>As well</hi> for the dignity of the Sacrament. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. Give not that which is holy to doggs, nor caſt your pearls before ſwine, for ſuch are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent perſons that continue in the filth of their ſin. <hi>As alſo</hi> for the danger that redoundeth unto them for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiving, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27. Who eateth and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>As alſo laſtly for the Communication of anothers ſin: of which a Miniſter makes himſelf partaker, that admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth notorious impenitent ſinners to this holy Banquet. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. Be not partakers of other mens ſins. Theſe are the words of <hi>Gerhard,</hi> unto which he adds the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chryſostme</hi> in his 83 <hi>Homily on Matth.</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that that zealous Father would rather loſe blood and life, then to the wounding of his conſcience admit unworthy perſons to the holy Supper, yea (ſaith he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) if the unclean were kept from the paſſeover. <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. 6. How much more are they that abide in the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118915:25"/> of great ſins; without true repentance, to be kept from the holy Supper. If one that is called a brother 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11. be a fornicator, &amp;c. with ſuch a one no not to eat, how much leſſe are they to be admitted to this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Banquet.</q> And ſo he goes on (as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> may read more then heart can wiſh, unto which he may add the peruſall of 22 and 23 <hi>chap.)</hi> and in <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>num.</hi> 251. <q>There was ſaith he in the antient Church a publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Publick ſcandalls: and a private confeſſion made to the Miniſter of the Church, that he might try the examination a man had made of himſelf, whether he did acknowledg his ſin with ſerious remorſe, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Chriſt with faith, and had a ſerious purpoſe to mend his life: for <hi>by this means</hi> (not by M. <hi>Prynns</hi> way) the <hi>impenitent</hi> were reformed, the <hi>negligent</hi> excited, the the <hi>rude</hi> inſtructed, the <hi>dejected</hi> were comforted with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical conſolation, and the <hi>unworthy uſe</hi> of the holy Supper was prevented. This is the large and faithful teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Gerhard.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Our own excellent <hi>Whitaker</hi> is larger then to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 94. <q>We muſt not ſay that he ears the body of Chriſt which is not in the body of Chriſt; for they cannot be accounted members of Chriſt; and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle further he addeth, He that comes without faith to the Sacraments, doth not onely, <hi>not beget grace,</hi> but doth make fearfull ſhipwrack of grace, and ſalvation: he that hath no <hi>faith receiveth damage by the Sacraments, but obtains not grace and ſalvation.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Hooker (Eccl. pol. lib.</hi> 5. Speaking largely of the Sacraments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I noted before,) <q>Saith, Sacraments are not phyſicall but moral inſtruments of ſalvation: duties of ſervice and worſhip; which unleſſe we perform as the Author of grace commandeth, they are unprofitable, for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118915:25"/> 
                  <hi>all receive not the grace of God that receive the Sacraments of his grace,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. George Geleſpie,</hi> did with his <hi>Arons Rod</hi> point to more learned, and better principles, then Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> had the happineſs to <hi>receive.</hi> I ſhall <hi>note</hi> him nothing in particular, but refer him to the book it ſelf, and the earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt peruſall of it <hi>once more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Feild lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. M. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Dr. <hi>Preſton, Calvin, Muſculus, Zanchie, Ameſius, Scharpius, Willet,</hi> Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews, Medit.</hi> Lord's Supper cap. 18. <hi>Reynalds.</hi> And lately the Reverend and moſt induſtrious Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and a very great number of other <hi>witneſſes</hi> of the truth of <hi>God, whoſe names are in the book of Life,</hi> might be produced: If the caſe required it, or this ſmal tract contain them.</p>
            <p>Onely I crave leave that I may produce <hi>one materiall witnes more,</hi> whilſt I muſt affront Mr. <hi>Prynne, Gentleman,</hi> (the <hi>Author</hi> of that Book, called, the <hi>perpetuity of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate mans eſtate,</hi> Printed 1626.) To Mr. <hi>Prynne Eſquire,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Scandalous pamphlet,</hi> now <hi>under cenſure.</hi> O that ever any mans <hi>vaſt abilities</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>blaſted,</hi> and <hi>dwindled</hi> into ſuch a pittifull <hi>piece of nothing,</hi> &amp; upon ſuch an <hi>unworthy</hi> (if not <hi>ungratious) ſubject,</hi> and in ſuch a <hi>ſcambling</hi> pamphlet.</p>
            <p>See whether he hath not don by us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what he then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of in others. Then he pitied the <hi>Puritan Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;</hi> now with <hi>Caligula</hi> he wiſhes ſurely <hi>wee had all but one neck, and at his mercy.</hi> He ſaith there in his Preface, <hi>There alwaies hath bin, are, and ſhall be a generation of men upon the earth, which ſhal be hated, ſcorned, perſecuted, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, reviled, accuſed, ſlandered, and condemned, even of all ſorts of men</hi> (&amp; <hi>for</hi> Mr. <hi>Prinn</hi>'s own worſhip) <hi>for no crime, no cauſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſin at all, but onely for their new, gratious, godly,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118915:26"/> 
               <hi>holy lives, and for their deteſt and hatred of all kind of Sin;</hi> (and amongſt other the ſin of prophaning the <hi>Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)</hi> ſuch were once his words; therefore,</p>
            <p>See I beſeech you the character that Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> then gave of us, and the <hi>contempt</hi> that now he caſts upon us.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Prin (Perpetuity: p.</hi> 344) <hi>ſaith, The Sacraments do never convey any inward, and ſpirituall grace, which may truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and ingraft man into Chriſt: But where there is a hand of faith to receive them, &amp; the grace conveyed by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Pag.</hi> 346. he ſaith, <hi>The Lords Supper is a cauſe of grace to none, but ſuch as receive in a worthy manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> (in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> and <hi>perpetuity pag.</hi> 348) calls this, <hi>an Arminian popiſh Doctrine; That the Sacraments do Ex opere operato convey grace to men, or that the bare act of Baptiſm, or receiveing the Lords Supper, ſhould of it ſelf without any reſpect of the perſons, and of the Sacraments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey grace to all that come unto them,</hi> ſo far Mr. <hi>pryn</hi> againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>Nay in this very Book <hi>(Lords Supper vind. pag.</hi> 58. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta conſiſtunt in eorum vſu,</hi> &amp;c. out of Ames) <hi>The Sacraments conſiſt properly in the uſe of them, ſo that a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is not a Sacrament, but in it's Sacramentall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it.</hi> doth then an unregenerate perſon receive it <hi>as a Sacrament?</hi> Doth he indeed Communicate <hi>really?</hi> and <hi>worthily receive</hi> the <hi>Body, and blood of Chriſt, with all the benefits of his death and paſſion,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his long aſſertion of it, <hi>pag.</hi> 39. for elſe if the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate <hi>receive</hi> not <hi>worthily,</hi> They <hi>receive</hi> not the body and blood of Chriſt <hi>at all,</hi> and ſo Mr. <hi>Prynn's</hi> great talk amounts onely to a <hi>nihil ſignificat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee willingly confeſſe, and imbrace what he ſaith out of Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> (that was (the world knowes) far from Mr.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118915:26"/> 
               <hi>Prynn's</hi> opinion as light from darkneſſe in this his tenent:) <hi>Our ſentence is, that the Sacraments have all efficacy in reſpect of grace, which a practicall ſoul can have, by any relation, but cannot effect grace immediatly, but by the mediation of the Spirit of God, and of Faith.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> ſhew us the <hi>relation,</hi> and the <hi>Faith</hi> of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſon; if not, let him not write <hi>crafts-maſter,</hi> over his ſo impertinent quotations. Or will M. <hi>Prinn</hi> apply that his <hi>Capitall</hi> quotation out of <hi>Jewell</hi> (to which <hi>true believers onely</hi> have a title) to the unregenerate alſo <hi>(By the partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ink whereof, we be revived, ſtrengthened, and fed unto immortality; and whereby we are joyned and incorporated into Chriſt, that we may abide in him, and he in us,</hi> &amp;c.) If Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> affirmeth, <hi>yea;</hi> that the unregenerate are here intended: he expreſsly oppoſeth <hi>Scripture, Fathers,</hi> and <hi>all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant writers,</hi> that I have <hi>ſeen,</hi> and as in ſome part I have <hi>cited.</hi> If it be <hi>nay;</hi> Then what doth ſo <hi>long a quotation,</hi> (of no leſſe then two pages) <hi>to ſo little purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true <hi>Jewell ſaith, the Sacraments do ſerve to aid and direct our faith.</hi> But where doth he (or any other Proteſtant) affirm, that they <hi>beget faith, where there was none at all before.</hi> Such a proof <hi>clear, and full, and backed with Scripture,</hi> would <hi>ſay ſomething:</hi> but all other affirmations (beneath that) are but <hi>clouds without water,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Prynns</hi> book but a <hi>Tree without fruit,</hi> and himſelf but like <hi>a raging Sea, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of his own ſhame,</hi> and his partners, whom I recommend to the peruſall of the laſt Paragraph
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118915:27"/> in his <hi>own Epiſtle,</hi> to thoſe who falſly, and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <hi>traduce, calumniate, and ſlander, (vid. Epiſt. to his Perpet.) you ſee now how ſcandalous, how ſlight, how falſe and forged, all theſe your accuſations are, you ſee they are but ſhifts to evade, and colours to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the truth, and ſuch as do profeſſe it and defend it they are but meer impoſtures, and pretences whereby the devil, and your own deceitfull hearts do labor for to blind your eyes, and to keep you still in darkneſs, to ſtupifie your hearts and conſciences, and ſo to ſet you in oppoſition againſt all grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> that ſo <hi>they may deprive you of your ſouls at laſt. Conſider who, and what it is that ſets you now on work to ſlander, and traduce the Saints of God, and to oppoſe his truth: and know, that it is not the God of peace and union, the God of grace and truth, but the very Devill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the very ſpirit of Antichrist, and the enemie of all grace and goodneſs, who out of ſome carnal wicked, ſiniſter, and by reſpests hath put you on this ſervice, ask but your own breaſts, and the ſecret whiſperings of your own conſciences, and they will tell you ſo. And therefore though I have ſpoken ſomewhat ſharply to you before, to make you know your ſelvs, (the want of which knowledg is the cauſe of all your errors) ſo now I do beſeech you by the mercyes of God, and by the death of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt your Saviour.</hi> And theſe words I ſay of Mr. <hi>Prynne (in diebus illis,)</hi> I do heartily commend to Mr. <hi>Prynne and his fellows now,</hi> in this day of their <hi>change,</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> againſt what they are <hi>changed from.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118915:27"/>
            <p> Finally I ſhall deſire both <hi>them, and my Fathers, and Brethren,</hi> to take it as my <hi>Prayer to God,</hi> and <hi>Apologie</hi> unto them all; what I ſhall only add, (as they may copiouſly find in the Concluſions of <hi>Peter Martyrs Tractate of the Supper, and of Beza's againſt Weſtphalus.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My prayer ſhall be <hi>Faxit autem Deus, The Lord grant of his goodneſs, that the Church of Chriſt may at the laſt obtain both peace and truth as to this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament! Which I wiſh, becauſe the Lords Supper hath been ſo injured, buried, and deformed, with lies, impoſtures, and ſuperſtitions, that one would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed rather think it any thing then that which the Lord inſtituted in his Supper: which leaſt we ſhould reform; the Devill, the grievious ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of all peace, and truth, hath ſown ſo many opinions, contentions, differences, hereſies, and conteſts, (onely not bloudy) that humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can ſcarce hope for a conſent worthy Chriſtians. But this alas is not onely our grief, for we lay a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reproach upon this Sacrament, for ſome of us rear an Idoll out of this excellent and ſingular gift of Chriſt: and others that have little ſincere faith, and a conſcience defiled with grievious ſins; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lawfull examination of our ſelvs, do even u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp the holy myſteries. The Lord pity this great calamity, and vouchſafe us at laſt the Eucharist reſtored to his Church, with the good uſe there of, even for our Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſake,</hi> Amen. vid. Tract. de Euchar ad finem.</p>
            <p>My Apology ſhall be in the words of <hi>Beza. Obteſtor vos omnes qui hanc Apologium eſtis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecturi, ego omnium infimus, ſerio tandem, non</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:118915:28"/> 
               <hi>quis ista incendia excitarit, ſed quâ tandem ratione, peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus extingui poſſint conſideremus. Plus ſatis eſt litium, plus ſatis convitiorum, plus ſatis criminationum, &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologiarum. (&amp; infra) neque vero quam haec ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, mihi in mentem venit, ut ego homuntio, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tantae doctrinae, &amp; Authoritatis homines, arbitri &amp; diſceptatoris partes agam. quis ſum enim ego, ut hanc cogitationem ſuſcipiam? Sed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quando ita tulit occaſio,</hi> QUIS MEUS SITANIMUS, &amp; Quae QUOTIDIANA SUS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PIRIA <hi>volui eccleſiae Dei Testari.</hi> I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thoſe that ſhall looke upon this Apologie, even I indeed the loweſt of you all, that wee may conſider, not who kindled theſe flames, but by what manner of way wee may thorowly quench them: there is too much ſtrife and railing, too many criminations and Apologies. neither whilſt I write theſe things have I any thought, that ſuch an inconſiderable perſon as my ſelfe, may take upon mee to be an Arbiter or Judg amongſt men of ſuch learning and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for who am I to have ſuch a thought? Yet becauſe the occaſion hath thus hapned, I have thought fit to teſtifie to the Church of God, what my mind is, and what my dayly prayers are.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Bookes Printed for</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt, <hi>at the Sign of the three Crowns,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Learned Commentary, or Expoſition upon the firſt Chapter of he ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Richard Sibbs,</hi> publiſhed for the publick good by <hi>Thomas Manton,</hi> Folio.</item>
               <item>The Journal or Diary of a thankfull Chriſtian: a Day-book of National and publick, perſonal and private paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Gods providence, to help Chriſtians to thankfulneſs, and experience. By <hi>John Beudle,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Barnſtone</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> large 8.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Robinſons</hi> Chriſtian Armor in large 8.</item>
               <item>Book of Emblems, with Latine and Engliſh verſes made upon <hi>(Lights)</hi> by <hi>Robert Farly,</hi> ſmall 8.</item>
               <item>A moſt Excellent Treatiſe concerning the way to ſeek Heavens Glory, to flye Earths vanity, to fear Hells horror, with godly prayers, and the Bell-mans ſummons, 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johnſons</hi> Eſſayes expreſſed in ſundry Exquiſite Fancies.</item>
               <item>The one thing neceſſary; By Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Stephens Walbrook,</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>Sion in the houſe of mourning, becauſe of Sin &amp; Suffering, being an Expoſition on the fifth Chapter of the <hi>Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> by D. S. Paſtor of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pingham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Rutland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Groane of the Spirit, or a Trial of the truth of Praier.</item>
               <item>A Handkercher for Parents Wet-eyes, upon the death of their Children or Friends.</item>
               <item>Four profitable Treatiſes very uſefull for Chriſtian pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; <hi>viz.</hi> The Killing power of the Law: The Spirituall Watch; The New Birth: Of the Sabbath. By the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>William Fenner,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Rochford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Peoples Need of a living Paſtor, at the ſunerall of Mr. <hi>John Frost,</hi> M. A. by Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Catechiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng God's Ordinance, in ſundry Sermons by Mr. <hi>Zachary Crofton.</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Buttolphs Aldgate London,</hi> the ſecond Edition corrected and augmented.</item>
               <item>A Coppy-book methodized and ingraven, by <hi>Thomas Croſſe,</hi> where in fair writing is expreſt, by which one may
<pb facs="tcp:118915:29"/> learn to write of himſelfe, that can but read.</item>
               <item>The godly mans Arke. in the day of his diſtreſſe, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in Divers Sermons, the firſt of which was preached at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Eliſabeth Moore.</hi> Whereunto is anexed Mrs. <hi>Eliſabeth Moores</hi> Evidences for Heaven, compoſed and collected by her in the time of her health, for her comfort in the time of ſickneſs, By <hi>Ed. Calamy,</hi> B. D. Paſtor of the the Church at <hi>Aldermanbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Enchiridion Judicum,</hi> or <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> Charge to his Judges.</item>
               <item>Together with <hi>Cataſtrophe Magnatum,</hi> or King <hi>David's</hi> Lamentation, at Prince <hi>Abners</hi> Incineration. By <hi>John Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſey</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Atherton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>There are going to the Preſs ſome new pieces of Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Fenners,</hi> late of <hi>Rochford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> never yet Printed, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by a ſpecial Providence, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of which is a Second part of his wilfull impenitency; being five Sermons more that he preached upon the 18. of <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiel,</hi> and the 32. ver.</item>
               <item>A theatre of flying Inſects, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cially the manner of right ordering the Bee is excellently deſcribed, with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes Hiſtorical and Phyſicall conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning them, with a Second part of meditations and obſervations Theological and Moral in 3 Centuries upon the ſame ſubject, by <hi>Samuel Purchas</hi> M. A. in 40.</item>
               <item>The Gale of oportunity and the Beloveb Deſciple by <hi>Thomas Froyſell.</hi> in 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> unvailed, with the Harmony of the Prophets Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; in which is reconciliation with God and his peopl. By <hi>William Guild.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Cotton,</hi> his practical Expoſition on the Firſt Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle of <hi>John,</hi> the ſecond Edition corrected, and inlarged.</item>
               <item>The Wedding Ring fit for the Finger: in a Sermon at a Wedding in <hi>Edmonton,</hi> by <hi>William Secker.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:30"/>
            <p>FInding my labors have found ſuch kind acceptance, &amp; ſuch good entertainment amongſt my honeſt Countrey men, it hath incouraged me this ſeventh time to write for their benefit, &amp; although this book may prove fruitleſs to many becauſe not underſtood, nor regarded; yet ſome few may be of that ſpirit, as to comprehend it &amp; imbrace it, if not openly profeſs it, yet ſecretly believe it, for upon my ſoul it is truth, written in love to thoſe that are afflicted with theſe diſtempers, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led New Diſeaſes: And I have taken up the Cudgils in defence of my Predeceſſor Dr. <hi>Culpepper,</hi> intending to amend his deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in point of Art, or better to finiſh where he left off: He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the Diſeaſes, &amp; I hope I ſhal ſtorm them, &amp; cauſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to fly or yeeld to my medicines; which medicines the Colledge if they pleaſe may uſe for the good health of poore Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Next I am to advertiſe you, that no books are printed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome faults: There is not a writer in the world, but if Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical fools will, he may find ſome fault or other with his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to carp at. Every man may look into himſelf before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes another; and whoſoever he be, let him either allow or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend anothers writing: I fear no mans raſh cenſure, nor will I plead for the Corrector and Compoſitor, the ingenuous have not onely judgment to diſcern, but courteſie to paſs by ſmal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faults. The moſt remarkable are theſe following.</p>
            <p>IN the Apologue l in. 18. r. <hi>prove.</hi> l. 20. r. <hi>my</hi> l. 26. r. <hi>Azotus.</hi> In the book, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 12. l. 7. r. <hi>Conarion.</hi> p. 37. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26. r. <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> p. 38. l. 1. r. <hi>D. Culpep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers Varlet,</hi> l. 15. add <hi>by Impoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs and Quacks that know not any th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in learning.</hi> p. 39. l. 18. r. <hi>which we have at wil,</hi> p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 7. r. <hi>Veagle.</hi> p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> p. 42. l. 26. r. <hi>theſe miſchiefs I ſhall preſcribe a cure.</hi> p. 44. l. 33. r. <hi>do not thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by E. A. I mean not Elias Aſhmolt.</hi> p. 46. l. 1. r. <hi>which taketh.</hi> p. 47. l. 30. r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming.</hi> P. 50. l. 29. for <hi>Booker,</hi> r. <hi>Cooper.</hi> p. 58. l. 9. r. <hi>this. l.</hi> 27. r. <hi>could t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them to their faces.</hi> p. 56. <hi>l.</hi> 30. r. <hi>torment many.</hi> p. 62. <hi>l.</hi> 10. de. <hi>in. l.</hi> 21. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E. Theodidact is. l.</hi> 27. <hi>r. Caſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118915:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
